<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Charity mistaken, with the want whereof, Catholickes are vniustly charged for affirming, as they do with grief, that Protestancy vnrepented destroies salvation.</title>
            <author>Knott, Edward, 1582-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837994</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837994</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2348</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15508)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2348)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1053:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Charity mistaken, with the want whereof, Catholickes are vniustly charged for affirming, as they do with grief, that Protestancy vnrepented destroies salvation.</title>
                  <author>Knott, Edward, 1582-1656.</author>
                  <author>Matthew, Tobie, Sir, 1577-1655, attributed author.</author>
                  <author>Potter, Christopher, 1591-1646.</author>
                  <author>Potter, Christopher, 1591-1646. Want of charitie justly charged.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 130, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Widow of C. Boscard],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed with licence, Anno 1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Edward Knott, the name Matthew Wilson adopted in 1602 and kept for the rest of his life.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Sir Tobie Matthew.</note>
                  <note>Answered by STC 20135: Christopher Potter. Want of charitie justly charged, 1633.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, line 7 of title ends "unrepen-", the preface is signed "):(2".</note>
                  <note>Title page stained; some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2348:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2348:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHARITY MISTAKEN, WITH THE WANT WHEREOF, <hi>Catholickes</hi> are vniuſtly <hi>charged:</hi> for affirming, as they do with <hi>grief,</hi> that <hi>Proteſtancy vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted destroies</hi> SALVATION.</p>
            <p>Printed with Licence, Anno 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:2348:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2348:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>HAVING obſerued the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, which men are growne to take, in not holding it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary to belieue that any one Religion is preciſely true; &amp; that for the excuſing of themſelues from blame, they thinke fit to lay the fault on others as being too ſtrict in approuing and vpholding only one; I haue thought fit to imply ſome of my houres vpon examining, how much or little reaſon they haue, in a caſe of this high impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, either to bragge of their owne charity, or to impeach the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ours. And therefore I ſhall humbly pray all my Proteſtant Readers, to bring attention without paſsion to the peruſall of this enſuing diſcourſe; wherein I will hope they ſhall meet with cauſe, to be as good to themſelues as I wiſh, or at leaſt to giue
<pb facs="tcp:2348:3"/>
ouer miſtaking vs, though perhaps<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſhall not care to mend themſelues. But certainly if there be any ſuch thing, as Heauen, and God, and Christ, and Faith, and Church, &amp; that indeed there be but one: not only ſhall they be miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men in the next life, vvho apply not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues intirely to the beliefe of that, and that alone; but they ſhall euen in this vvorld be vvorthily held ignorant and imprudent, vvho taxe men as vncharitable for nothing but becauſe they approue not many. For let that, vvhich follovveth, be vvell vveighed; and they vvill ſee that not only Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes affirme this truth; but that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe there of is alſo auowed both by the practiſe and principles of the chief Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants themſelues in their vvritings; hovvſoeuer the contrary diſcourſe raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth too much in the minds and mouths of particular men of that profeſsion, vvho haue many times ſo much of the good fellovv, that they haue too little of the good Chriſtian. But I remit my ſelfe to that, vvich follovves: vvhich againe I recommend to the Reader.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2348:3"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>THAT CATHOLICKS ARE both improbably and vniustly charged with lacke of Charity, for affirming that Protestancy vnrepented de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyes ſaluation. <hi>CHAPTER I.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it be a part of honour and iuſtice, for a Cauallier of this world, to defend the rights of the oppreſſed; and to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, if there be cauſe, with particular care, towards the protection and defenſe of ſome excellent, but afflicted Lady, whoſe fame were blaſted by the ill to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues of men: how much more iuſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable will it be for a Catholike (who in this time and place, may well goe for a Cauallier of Chriſt) to defend the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and fame of his Lady and Mother, which is the holy Catholicke Church: Shee being ſo innocent, as the immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Spouſe of Chriſt our Lord ought to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2348:4"/>
be, and yet with all, ſo much wronged, as to be taxed for wanting the very wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ringe, and the nuptiall to be it ſelfe of <hi>Charity,</hi> whereby ſhee is beſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from all pretenders to that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage bed, and moſt euidently marked out to be that very Spouſe, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhee is? For, that the abounding in Charity ſhould be the diſtinctiue ſigne of the Church of Chriſt our Lord, from euery other congregation vpon earth, he did by the Oracle of his owne bleſſed mouth declare expreſſely vpon record; when ſpeaking to the ſame Spouſe of his, in the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his diſciples he ſayd thus; <hi>By this shal all men know,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euan. Io. c. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>whether you be my diſciples or no, if you loue one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And leaſt by occaſion of theſe words, a man might chance to thinke, that the Church were only bound to loue her owne children, and conſequently that Catholicks were but obliged to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine Charity towards their fellow Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks; our Lord did elſwhere teach vs, that we were not only to loue our <hi>friends,</hi> but our <hi>enemyes</hi> alſo, by his owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>bestowing his ſunne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. c. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>and rayne, not only vpon the iuſt, but vpon the vniust alſo;</hi> and that it was to be a ſigne of a true Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2348:4"/>
                  <hi>if he were ready euen to lay downe his life for his ſlocke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> whereby in this caſe the ſpirituall good, of no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole world, is to be vnderſtood. So that to charge the Catholicke Church, that ſhee proceeds vncharitably towards Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants; and that ſo far, as through the want thereof, to cenſure and condemne them to the paynes of hell; is as good (as hath bene ſaid) as to tell her to her teeth, that ſhe is but a harlot and ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and not indeed the Spouſe of Chriſt, as ſhe pretends. And now therefore I, as a childe, though an vnworthy one, of this Church, feeling the affront which his mother vndergoes vpon this occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, will procure to remoue it the beſt I can; and in the firſt place to ſhew, how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable the ſlander is; and in the ſecond place, how vntrue.</p>
               <p>Firſt then at the very firſt fight, it is wholy improbable, euen ſuppoſing that the Catholicke Church ſhould vniuſtly &amp; vntruly hold (as ſhee is charged by her aduerſaries to doe) that Proteſtancy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repented deſtroyes ſaluation, that yet this ſhould be affirmed by her, through want of Charity, and not rather vpon ſome other motiue, namely error in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2348:5"/>
indiſcreet zeale of ſoules, immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate feare of the iuſtice of God, or the like. For to ſee the holy Catholicke Church diſſolue, and euen as it were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feate her ſelfe of her very ſelfe, for the acquiring of all imaginable both tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and eternall bleſſing to mankinde; &amp; then yet to ſay, that becauſe ſhee wants Charity, ſhee will not allow men of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Religions a place in heauen, where yet there is roome inough for all the world; doth ſtampe the marke of abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity vpon the very front of the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, euen whileſt it is deliuered. Now to ſee that this Catholicke Church is, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a moſt eminent manner, ſo expreſſiue, &amp; diffuſiue of her ſelfe towards the good of others, as hath bene ſayd, a man needes no more but to haue eyes in his head; for the truth thereof is not only to be eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by reaſon, but it lies ſubiect euen to common ſence, and to the obſeruation of euery ordinary looker on. For what kinde of creature is there, of what condition, what ſex, what age, whom the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church doth not ſtriue to wrap vp in the bowels of her pitty? &amp; how reſtles is that ſolicitude wherwith ſhee doth it?</p>
               <p>As ſoon as any childe is borne, ſhee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2348:5"/>
conſidering the preciſe neceſſity of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, will be ſure to initiate him with that Sacrament; wherin other Religions are farre more remiſſe. When he growes vp to yeares of diſcretion, ſhee ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s him with the Sacrament of Conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. When ſhee findes him once to haue drunke of the poyſoned cup of actual ſin, ſhee ſtriues to make him caſt it vp againe, by the Sacrament of Confeſſion and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. To the end that he may not only enioy ſome proportion of health, but be able to ſtand out, and grow, and paſſe on with ſtrength and comfort, ſhee feedes him from time to time, with the pretious Body of our bleſſed Lord in the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, of the Altar. If he will beſtow himſelfe vpon the ſeruice of Almighty God in a more particular manner, by taking Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, ſhe not only giues him holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, but ſhe doth it by a Sacrament co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring grace. If he haue not ſpirit for ſo much as that, but reſolues to walke on in the broade way of a marryed life; that ſtate is honorable, though it be inferiour to the former; and ſhe ioynes him to a wife, by a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferring grace. If in his laſt ſicknes he be aſſalted by thoſe ſharpeſt arrowes of his inuiſible
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2348:6"/>
enemy, ſhe annoynts him towards the combat, &amp; enables him by that Extreme Vnction, and by the benedictions and prayers which accompany it, to reſiſt &amp; conquer thoſe aduerſe powers. When he is giuing vp the ghoſt ſhe recomends the ſoule with moſt tender, and affectuall words, into the hands of God. And it is no ſooner diſcharged from that body, but inſtantly ſhe makes it her buſineſſe, to pray for it; and ſtill ſhe prayes, and prayes, and neuer giues it ouer till the worldes end.</p>
               <p>But now in the meane time, whileſt Chriſtians are leading this mortall life, for ſuch as haue a deſire to conſecrate themſelues wholy to God in any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Order, by the vowes of Pouerty, Chaſtity, and Obedience, whether they be men, or women, the holy Catholicke Church with exceſſiue Charity, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uides meanes for them, in Monaſteries, and other Religious houſes, (either by the foundations of Princes and great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or els by the ordinary and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Charities of her deuout children in generall) that they may be enabled to liue, and wholly attend to that ſacred fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for the aſſiſtance of mankinde in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2348:6"/>
the way of ſpirit (though ſome after a more contemplatiue, and ſome others after a more actiue or mixed manner) without ſcattering, or diſperſing their thoughts and cares, vpon prouiding for the neceſſaries of this life.</p>
               <p>She doth alſo otherwiſe finde meanes, that ſecular men &amp; woemen be ſuccou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, according to all theyr miſeries, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be ſpirituall or temporall. If men be to ſuffer as malefactors, ſhe hath children, who by ſpeciall deuotion oblige themſelues to watch ſome nights with thoſe poore creatures, of what Religion ſoeuer they may be, to prepare them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they dye, for that great paſſage, If men be taken priſoners by Moores, or Turkes, or other Infidels, ſhe nouriſhes whole Orders of Religious people in her boſome, whoſe office it is to keep cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence in thoſe other vnbelieuing parts; by meanes whereof the miſerable creatures are redeemed, and reſtored to their former liberty, through the Charity of her children. Orphanes, and poore virgins are brought vp by thouſands; and endowed with marriage money. And perſons ſicke of all diſeaſes, are cheriſhed and relieued, and regaled by whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2348:7"/>
(as man may ſay) of Chriſtians, in her Hoſpitalls: yea &amp; they are ſerued and attended (after the example of Chriſt our Lord) by the owne hands of great Princes and Prelates, &amp; of choice &amp; deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Ladies, &amp; Queenes, in the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the holy Catholicke Church.</p>
               <p>But then, as much as ſoules are more worth then bodies, ſo farre doth the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Catholicks, for the inſtructing, &amp; gayning ſoules, exceed thoſe former Charities, which they impart for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of mens bodies. For where there is queſtion of bringing vp youth in vertue; of drawing ignorant and dull people to ſome reaſonable proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of knowledge in thinges belonging to their ſaluation; of reducing men, who are peruerted by hereſy; of conuerting men, who are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed quicke in the blindenes of infidelity; what paynes, what care, what vaſt iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys both by ſea and land, what incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, what danger, what torment, what death is not moſt gladly vndergone and euen deſired by worlds of Religious men, who are children of the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church; and who ſucke the ſweet ſtrong ſpirit of the loue of martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, from the breſts of their mother;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2348:7"/>
ſhe being inſpired and inriched there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, by her celeſtiall ſpouſe? In the ſtrength whereof, they bleſſe ſuch as curſe them; they pray for ſuch as perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them; and are ready vpon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in the hope of freeing their enemies from damnation, to runne hazard of their owne temporall death. Now ſhe who is ſo profuſe in affoarding fauours, will be ſure preciſe in not doing wrongs. And ſo it is notorious to the whole world (as appeares both by our innumerable books of Caſes of conſcience, and by thoſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mularies alſo, which are dayly ſet out to inſtruct and teach men how to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine themſelues, and to confeſſe their ſinnes) that ſhe is moſt ſtrict in keeping vs, from iudging or ſpeaking vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of any one, and from doing men the leaſt wronge, either in thought, word or deed. And now without recrimmating vpon our aduerſaries, for the want of ſuch great charities, and diligences as theſe, mee thinkes I may appeale eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, whether it be euen probable (as I ſayd before) that the belief of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church, concerning the ill eſtate of ſuch as dy impenitent in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, can be thought to proceed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2348:8"/>
from want of <hi>Charity,</hi> and deſerue not rather to be imputed, and aſcribed, to ſome other cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the intention of Catholicks when they ſay that Protestancy vnrepented de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyes ſaluation, and how the ſpeech is to be vnderſtood. <hi>CHAPTER II.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe intention therefore, wherwith Catholicks declare that Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vnrepented deſtroyes ſaluation, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with any colour of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be thought to proceed from want of <hi>Charity</hi> in them, but indeed from the religious and iuſt care they haue to awake men toward the ſauing of theyr ſoules, in the right way; by procuring that they ſee, that they are to periſh, if they continue in the wrong. And the good God of heauen doth beſt know, that when we ſpeake to Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in this kinde, our very hearts are ſad, as conſidering how true it is, and how much it imports them to weigh it well; and that yet, the while, in ſteed of theyr proffiting by our aduice, they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne vs for preſenting it to them in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2348:8"/>
beſt ſorte we can.</p>
               <p>Nay they calumniate not only our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, as hath bene ſayd, by affirming that it proceeds in vs from want of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;</hi> but they charge vs withall, with taking the office of Almighty God out of his hands, by pronouncing iudgment v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our fellow ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts before their time; and in fine, that we make their Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to be as the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which is not capable of any remiſſion at the hands of God.</p>
               <p>But the Caſe being well conſidered, will appeare to be ill put againſt vs, who are farre from being liable to ſuch aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as theſe. Wee iudge not them or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other: for we know that we all muſt ſtand, or fall to our owne Maſter. We loue their perſons, and we pitty them for their errors; and we proceed no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe towards them, then as towards creatures who are made after the image of Almighty God, and who were redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the death and Paſſion of our one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> and we pray and hope, that before they part out of this life, the merits of the ſaid death &amp; paſſion of our Bleſſed Lord may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to theyr ſoules, by fayth and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2348:9"/>
and penance, &amp; by thoſe Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and other conduits &amp; meanes of conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and applying his grace, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual life to their ſoules, which are onely to be found in the boſome of the holy Catholicke Church. Without which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and other meanes, the merits and blood of Chriſt our Lord, though moſt apt and able in themſelues, to ſaue a thouſand millions of worlds, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſaue any one ſoule. For in fine, the merits of our Lord, and the ſinfull ſoules of men, be two extreames of great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from one another; &amp; can neuer be brought to meet, but by ſuch wayes and meanes, as the vnſpeakeable power and wiſedome &amp; goodnes of Almighty God, hath found out for that purpoſe; and thoſe meanes are they, which I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready touched. For if the merit of our Bleſſed Sauiours death, were of it ſelfe to ſaue any one ſoule, without the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation thereof by the aforeſaid meanes; no reaſon at all could be aſſigned, why any one ſoule ſhould be loſt; as yet the farre greatet part of ſoules is ſure to be.</p>
               <p>So that we ſpeake not ſo much of Proteſtants in thy kind as of the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of hereſy which they follow, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2348:9"/>
we iudge no more of them vpon this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but that whileſt they liue in that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, they eſtrange themſelues from the right meanes of applying the merits of Chriſt our Lord to theyr ſoules, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might be ſaued. But yet we hope neuertheles, that God will haue ſo much mercy on many of them, before they dy, as to incorporate them into his myſticall body, which is his true Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may partake the influence of that mercy and grace, which is deriued from the head thereof <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord. And therefore it is plaine, that we make not Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy to be at a ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which cannot be forgiuen, becauſe it will not be repented; whereas Proteſtancy both may, and often is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, and conſequently forgiuen: &amp; to the end that it may be ſo, we declare the grieuouſnes of the ſinne, and we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure by all the meanes, we can, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue the ſame.</p>
               <p>Nay, we are ſo farre from accounting it a ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, as that by our ſaying that Proteſtancy vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted excludes ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we imploy no more, then meerly, that it is a mortall ſinne. For whoſoeuer dyes impenitent of any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2348:10"/>
one mortall ſinne can neuer be ſaued,<note place="margin">S. Paul ad Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</note> and whoſoeuer ſhall with true penance be ſory and depart from his Proteſtancy, though it be but in the laſt minute of his life, will be capable of ſaluation. So that we iudge not men in particular, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their ſaluation of damnation; but yet on the other ſide, we muſt not be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayd to affirme (though we are cordial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſory for hauing cauſe to doe it) that they who dye impenitent either of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancy, or any other ſinne which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priues the ſoule of the grace of God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaued. For ſuch men as theſe, are iudged already in generall, by the mouth of God; but which of them in his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, ſhall be taken before he dy out of that vnhappy hearde of goates, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in that bleſſed flocke of ſheepe, by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the good ſhepheard, we leaue to his owne vnſearcheable determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And therfore as we take not the office of Iudge out of his hand; becauſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come to know whether this or that particular ſinner may not repent before he dye: ſo yet we may ſafely ſay, that a man, who liues in Proteſtancy, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mortall ſinne; and who is ſo farre from repenting it (though he be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2348:10"/>
informed thereof) as that he will not ſo much as acknowledge it to be a ſinne; and who, (for ought we know, or canne learne) did no way retract or reuerſe it, ſo much, as at the hower of his death; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts this life in a ſtate which is greatly to be lamented: and withall that if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented himſelfe as little of it indeede, &amp; in the ſight of God, as in our ſight he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to doe, there canne be no doubt with vs (ſo longe as we beleeue our Religion to be true) but that ſuch a perſon dyed without ſaluation, as departing in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate profeſſion of a different Religion, which we eſteeme to be falſe. And the ſame muſt they alſo beleeue of vs, <hi>mutatis mutandis,</hi> if indeede they beleeue their owne Religion to be true Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, of which Chriſt himſelfe pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. <hi>Qui non crediderit condemnabitur.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2348:11"/>
               <head>That our ſaying that Proteſtancy vnrepented destroyes ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, proceedes from want of Charitie in vs, is no leſſe vntrue (becauſe there is but one true Church,) then alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy I haue shewed it to be improbable, and firſt this is proued by holy ſcripture. <hi>CHAPTER III.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HItherto I haue been ſhewing how vtterly improbable it is, euen <hi>prima facie,</hi> that we ſhould cenſure Proteſtancy or Proteſtants, through want of <hi>Charitie;</hi> and withall what that motiue is, which induces vs to let them know the extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of danger, wherein they are; or that when we hold any ſuch diſcourſe, it is ſo farre from being an effect of want of <hi>Charitie</hi> in vs towards them, as that it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceedes from our deepe compaſſion of their caſe, which is the moſt ſweete &amp; pretious fruite of that ſoueraigne vertue. My endeauour now ſhal be, to ſhew that this charge of vncharitablenes, againſt vs is not only improbable, but vniuſt alſo &amp; vntrue. And that in carrying our ſelues herein as we doe, we not only not ſwarue from our duty to them; but if we ſhould
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2348:11"/>
doe otherwiſe, we ſhould fayle of that obedience which we owne to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God himſelfe, who exacts the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this office, at the handes of his holy Catholicke Church. And now for the clearing of this point in ſuch ſort as that it may ſatisfie doubtfull mindes, it will firſt be fit to premiſe ſome few groundes, vpon which I may the better build vp that truth, which I am about to declare.</p>
               <p>I will not offer here to prooue, that there is a God; becauſe now I haue not to doe which <hi>profeſſed Atheiſtes:</hi> nor yet that Chriſt our Lord is the true ſonne of God, who ſuffered death for the redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world; becauſe we liue not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Iewes.</hi> But for as much as there are ſuch differences of opinion, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that Religion and Church, which was founded and framed by Chriſt our Lord: I will briefely ſhew in the firſt place, that Almighty God did found one Church, and but one; and that he ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned one Religion, wherein he would be ſerued, and but one; and that out of that Communion there is no ſaluation. In the ſecond place I will make it appeare, that the vnity which is to be maintained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2348:12"/>
the members of this one true Church, and the profeſſors of this one Religion, is directly broken betweene Catholickes and Proteſtants. And then I make account, that in the third place, it will follow euen of it ſelfe, that both Catholicks and Proteſtants are not ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in both their ſeueral Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance thereof. And conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that no one of vs is to be blamed, if conceauing his owne to be the only true Religion, he declare the dangerous eſtate, wherein he takes any other man to be, who communicates and agrees not with him; but rather that he is obliged to let him know it. And now I will briefely put my ſelfe to proue the firſt aſſertion concerning the unity of the Church, by ſome texts &amp; teſtimonies of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and firſt of the old Teſtament.</p>
               <p>In the time of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Almighty God to draws a viſible people to himſelfe, and to give them an expreſſe law; and to ordaine varietie of viſible ſacrifices, by the oblation whereof they were to doe him homage, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe his wrath; and to inſtitute viſible ceremonies for the more deuout and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act performance of the ſame, it was alſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2348:12"/>
pleaſing to his diuine Maieſty to appoint, that howſoeuer the Iewes were to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſome kinds, in their ſeueral Synagogues, yet that ſacrifice was not to be offered to him by them, but in the only Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> He alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded; that in ſuch caſes of difficulty, as might occure; his whole people ſhould be ſubiect to the determination and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of the high Prieſt for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and this,<note place="margin">Deut. cap. 17.</note> vpon no leſſe then the paine of death; from which ſentence there was to be no appeale. Let the place at large be well conſidered, and it will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare by the great authority, and power, which was caſt vpon the indiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual perſon of one Iudge; that there could neither be any other Church, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religion which might pretend to be true, if it would preſume to diſagree, &amp; diſſent from this.</p>
               <p>The ſame truth is alſo made euident, by the feareful iudgment, which fell vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Core, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiron,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 16.</note> for theire act of diſobedience againſt <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> in ſo much as that the ground opened it ſelfe, and ſwallowed them vp aliue, with all their goods, into the profound pit of hell, in the ſight of the whole paople;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2348:13"/>
for but offering to make a ſchiſme from that one Church, wherein he had ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned himſelfe to be ſerued.</p>
               <p>According to this practiſe vnder the written lawe, Almighty God ſpeaking to the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> of the times which were to ſucceede vnder the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias,</hi> made a promiſe that he would giue true Chriſtians a heart which ſhould be moſt truly one.<note place="margin">Ezech. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Et dabo eis cor vnum.</hi> And the kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> deſcribes the excellency, and Maieſtie of Almightie God, by declaring <hi>howe he raignes in his holy place; and makes them who inhabite that houſe, to be all after one manner, and to be indued with the ſame affections and dictame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s concerning his ſeruices.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal, 67.</note> 
                  <hi>Deus in loco ſancto ſuo, qui inhabitare facit vnius moris in domo.</hi> Thoſe words alſo of the <hi>Canticles; Vna eſt columba mea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>perfecta mea, &amp;c.</hi> were ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the holy Ghoſt, in the perſon of God the Father, with intention to deſigne &amp; delineate, the vnity of the Church: for ſo it is interpreted by S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De vnit. Ecleſ.</note> and he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes himſelfe further thus, vpon that occaſion; <hi>will any man thinke that he holds fast his faith if he hold not faſte this vnity of the Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the ſame alſo is deliuered; at leaſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2348:13"/>
as certainely, in the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; and ſo much more euidently, and aboundantly, as the Church of God vnder the lawe of grace, was to be farre more diffuſed ouer the whole world, and both for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Chriſt our Lord, &amp; the ſafety of his ſeruants, who were ſo dearely bought by himſelfe to be preſerued in no leſſe perfect vnity the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer it had enioyed in former times. We ſee therfore that Chriſt our Lord made it one of his laſt ſuits to his eternall father (when he ſtood, as it were, euen vpon the very brim of death) <hi>that he would preſerue the diſciples whom he had giuen him, he would make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>as truly one</hi> in affection and will touching things with might concerne his ſeruice, <hi>as euen the Father &amp; Son were one.</hi> And it may be noted here with all, that in this caſe, he ſpeakes to his eternall Father for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of comfort, with a compellation of extraordinary tendernes, ſaying,<note place="margin">Io. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Pater ſancte, ſerua eos. &amp;c. Keep them, holy Father &amp;c.</hi> to ſhew, how much his hearte was ſet vpon this ſuite. When alſo he was vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the point of his <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, he commaunded his diſciples to <hi>teach all nations to obſerue all thoſe things whatſoeuer, which he hadu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commaded them;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 18 v. 9. 20.</note>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2348:14"/>
and he pronounced indefinitely, <hi>that whoſoeuer would not belieue, shouldbe conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:</hi> which doth clearely relate, not only to this or that particular Article, but to the whole ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of Chriſtian doctrine in generall: and thus it may be ſeene, that he intended to ordaine an exacte vnity in his Church;<note place="margin">Marc. 16 v. 26.</note> &amp; that whoſoeuer ſhould fayle of beleeuing any one point of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doctrine; ſhould be as ſure of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, as if he had beleeued but any one, or none.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles planted this one faith, and watered it with all ſo well, that our Lord gaue great encreaſe to it, &amp; the holy Ghoſt declared, in the acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,<note place="margin">Act. 4,</note> 
                  <hi>That the whole multitude of belieuers had but one heart and one ſoule.</hi> And that <hi>veſſell of the holy Ghost, S. Paule,</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how very much this point of vnity did import, ſendes his aduiſe to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 4.</note> that they ſhould <hi>be carefull to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the vnity of the ſpirit, in the bond of peace;</hi> and the word whereby he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes himſelfe, implyes no ordinary kinde of care, but a moſt <hi>particular ſolicitude of minde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould neuer make an ende, if I would preſſe all thoſe places of the new
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2348:14"/>
Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which declare the intention of our Lord to haue his Church one, and only one. The very names, whereby it is deſcribed, as for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple that of the <hi>Arcke of Noe; of one Kingdome; one Cittie; one Spouſe; one vineyard; one fielde; one barne; one ship; one net; one body;</hi> &amp; many others of like nature, which I omit; ſhewe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly that the Church of Chriſt our Lord, was to be but <hi>One.</hi> And eſpecially this point was ſetled by our Lord, when he made his owne Church, to be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupreame Iudge euen in all ſpirituall offences and ſcandalls, and much more in Controuerſies of Religion amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; requiring, that <hi>whoſoeuer would not hearken to, and obey that Church should be held a very Pagan, and Publican;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 18.17.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out allowing him ſoe much as any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale at all, euen to the holy Scripture it ſelfe. By which only words of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord; it is moſt clearly &amp; naturally prooued, that this Church is enriched, with thoſe very qualities, and markes which are auowed by vs her children, &amp; conteſted by the aduerſaries thereof; as namely with a <hi>perpetuall viſibility;</hi> or els he had giuen vs a commaunde which it were not poſſible for vs to obey. For
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2348:15"/>
how ſhould we at all times find out, and conſulte our difficulties, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints to that Church, which at all times could not be ſeene by the eyes of men, with a moſt <hi>certaine infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility?</hi> For otherwiſe, a man might periſh for beleeuing and profeſſing falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, through his obedience to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundant of Chriſt our Lord, in ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to an erring Church. But eſpecially (which makes moſt to our purpoſe) the <hi>entire vnity of the Church</hi> is prooued here, by the exact obedience, which we are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to exhibite to the ſame Church. For els, if there might be two ſeuerall true <hi>Churches</hi> diſſenting from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they might holde me <hi>for a Publican and Pagan,</hi> if I did not obey them both: which were impoſſible for me to doe, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunding contrary things. And if one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſſented from the other I muſt be toſſed betwixt two damnations. For if I ſhould obey that true Church er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, I ſhould incurre damnation by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying her, and by embracing and perſiſting in her errours; &amp; yet if I ſhould not obey her I ſhould incurre damnation by the expreſſe ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt our Lord himſelfe, who appoints me to be held a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2348:15"/>
Pagan, if I obey her not. And this ſhall ſuffice for this Chapter, wherein we may haue ſeen, what holy Scripture ſaith to this queſtion: and in the next we ſhall find, that the Fathers of the Primitiue Church, who follow it as their guide, will not fayle to vtter the ſame voice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The expreſse vnity of the Church is prooued by the authority of the Fathers of the most primitiue times. <hi>CHAPTER IIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe holy Fathers in the moſt primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue times, who are iuſtly called <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and reuerenced as ſuch by vs, were yet withall moſt obedient and humble children, to the holy <hi>Catholicke Church</hi> of their time; and ſo treading in thoſe very ſteps, which had beene traced out for them by the holy Ghoſt in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they haue ſhewed many wayes, how they beleeued and knewe, that there was but <hi>one true Church,</hi> and that the perfect <hi>vnity</hi> thereof, was to be ſo very carefully maintained, as that whoſoeuer broke it, muſt euerlaſtingly periſh.</p>
               <p>I ſay they haue ſhewed many wayes,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2348:16"/>
what their <hi>dictamen</hi> was herein: for ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whole books, expreſly and to no other end at all, but to prooue the neceſſity of <hi>vnity</hi> in the Church of Chriſt our Lord; as namely <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> and <hi>S. Auguſtine.</hi> Others haue written, &amp; framed expreſſe Catalogues of all the hereſyes which had riſen in the Church of Chriſt our Lord from his Aſcenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> til their own time; expreſly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hereby, that both the <hi>vnity</hi> of the Church was directly broken by the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate beliefe of any one doctrine, which was held in diſobedience to the ſame Church; and withall, that whoſoeuer did ſo breake it, muſt forfet the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſoule thereby. And this was doone by <hi>S. Epiphanius Bishop of Cyprus, by Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtrius Bishop of Breſcia,</hi> both who are ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to this purpoſe by the incomparable <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> in his treatiſe <hi>de hereſibus ad Quod vult Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Where himſelf alſo maks an exact Catalogue of all the hereſies which had ſprung vntill his time: and where, by the way, I muſt needs obſerue in a word, that he recou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts diuers hereſies, which are held by the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Church at this day, and particularly that <hi>of deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prayers and ſacrifices for the dead;</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2348:16"/>
then he concludes in the end, that <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer should hold any one of them, were not Chriſtian Catholick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides this way of proofe, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>vnity</hi> of the Church; I will alſo cite the Fathers who are full of expreſſe and poſitiue texts, whereby vpon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they proue the <hi>vnity</hi> of the Church, and I will begin with <hi>S. Ireneus,</hi> who diſcourſes thus.<note place="margin">Lib. 1. cap. 3. Hac prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>The Church hauing</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this word preached, and this faith, as was ſhewed before, and hauing ſpred the ſame ouer the whole world, doth diligently preſerue it, as inhabiting one houſe; and doth likewiſe beleeue thoſe thinges which are taught thereby, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one ſoule &amp; one heart, &amp; in the ſame conformity, ſhe preaches and teaches, &amp; deliuers it, as indeed poſſeſſing but one mouth. For though there be in the world different expreſſions, &amp; tongues, yet the vertue and power of <hi>Tradition</hi> is but <hi>one,</hi> and the ſame. And neither thoſe Churches which are found in <hi>Germany,</hi> nor thoſe others in <hi>Spaine,</hi> nor thoſe in <hi>France,</hi> nor they which are in the <hi>Easterne parts,</hi> nor they which are in <hi>Egypt,</hi> nor they which are in <hi>Libya,</hi> nor they which ar ſetled in the middle parts of the world,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2348:17"/>
doe beleeue or make traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of doctrine, any otherwiſe in one place the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in another. But as that creature of God, the <hi>Sunne,</hi> is one and the ſame in the whole world, ſo is the preaching of the truth, a light which ſhews euery wheare, and illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates all men who will come to the knowledge of the truth. And thoſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of Churches, who haue moſt power and grace of ſpeache, will deliuer no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things but theſe. For <hi>noe man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his maiſter,</hi> neither will ſuch an one as hath meaner talents in ſpeach, make this doctrine and <hi>Tradition</hi> leſſe; but ſince <hi>Faith</hi> is but <hi>one,</hi> and the ſame; neither doth he inlarge it, who is able to ſpeake much of it; nor that other diminiſh it, whoe ſpeakes leſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">De prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus &amp;c.</note>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſhewes plainly, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer denyes any <hi>one</hi> doctrine of the Church reiecteth all, for thus he ſayeth vpon occaſion. <hi>Valentinus approueth ſome things of the law and the Prophets; ſome things be diſavowes; that is, be diſallowes all, whilest he approues ſome.</hi> And the ſame <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. c. 8. Caeteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multos &amp;c.</note> doth alſo elſwhere, in the ſame booke inferre, the truth of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke doctrine, by the exacte <hi>vnity</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whileſt he ſayth after this manner.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2348:17"/>
                  <hi>Quod apud multos &amp;c. That which is found to be</hi> one, <hi>amongst ſoe many, is not to be thought to haue crept in by errour, but to haue beene recommended by Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Cirill</hi> Patriarche of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Catech. 18.</note> aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning reaſons why the Church of Chriſt our Lord is called <hi>Catholicke,</hi> doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently giue this one, amongſt the reſt; <hi>Quia docet Catholicè id est vniuerſaliter,</hi> &amp;c <hi>Becauſe she teacheth Catholickely, that is to ſay, vniuerſally and without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or difference, all thoſe doctrines, which ought to be knowne, concerning things either viſible or inuiſible, celeſtiall or terreſtriall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> in his booke <hi>de vnitate Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae,</hi> ſayeth thus,<note place="margin">Eccleſia Domini luce per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſa &amp;c.</note> of the <hi>vnity</hi> of the Church. <hi>The Church being ſtroken through by the</hi> light of our Lord doth ſende her beams throughout the whole world; but yet that light, which is caſt ſo far abroad, is but one, and the ſame; ſhe ſpreads her brannches, ouer the whole earth after a plentifull manner; ſhe extendes her flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtreames with greate abundance, &amp; to a great diſtance; but yet is ſhe one head and one roote, and one mother, who is fruitfull by ſuch ſtore of iſſue.<note place="margin">Lib. 1. Epiſt. 6.</note> The ſame Saint alſo, ſpeaking of the ſin of <hi>Core, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> and <hi>Abiron</hi> implies that the <hi>one</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2348:18"/>
Church muſt not only be entirely belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but followed alſo, in all her doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and directions. For he ſaieth that though <hi>Core, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiron,</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue and worſhip <hi>one</hi> God, and liued in the ſame law, and religion with <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> yet becauſe they deuided the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the reſt by Schiſme, reſiſting their gouernours and Prieſts, they were ſwallowed vp quick into hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Baſile</hi> puts ſuch a value vpon the abſolute integrity of all the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine, (which declares what he belieued concerning the neceſſity of <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in the Church) as to expreſſe himſelfe after this manner.<note place="margin">S. Baſil. apud Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret. l. 4. hiſt. c. 17. Qui in ſacris litteris &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>They who are well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in holy writ, permit not one ſyllable of diuine doctrine to be betrayed, or yeelded vp; but are willing to embrace any kind of death, for the defence thereof, if neede require.</hi> That man of God, had beene ſolicited by ſome to relent for a time, and to yeeld though it were but to a litle; he refuſed in ſuch ſort as you haue ſeene &amp; he did it much diſdaine to be atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in that kind.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Gregory Nanzianzene</hi> ſpeaking of Hereticks, who doe all breake the <hi>vnity</hi> of the Church; ſeemes yet to apprehend them to be worſte of all, who whileſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2348:18"/>
indeed they breake it,<note place="margin">Greg. Nazian. Tract de fide. Nihil pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſius &amp;c, Lib. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po. cont. Ruff. Propter vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c.</note> doe yet ſeeme to doe it leaſt; becauſe ſo they will hardlieſt be perceaued. And he deliuers himſelfe in theſe words. <hi>Nothing can be more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, then thoſe Heretikes, who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they runne ſtreight through all the reſt, doe yet with one word, as with ſome drop of poiſon, infect the true and ſincere faith of our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſhewes, that the <hi>vnity</hi> of the Church, and faith thereof, muſt be ſo perfect; as that <hi>for ſome one word or two, contrary to the ſame, many hereſies haue been caste out of the Church.</hi> And <hi>S. Leo</hi> ſaith, <hi>that out of the Catholicke Church there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pure, according to that of the Apostle; whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne:</hi> and els where he ſaith alſo. <hi>If it be not</hi> one, <hi>it is no faith at all.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning this <hi>one Church, S. Augustine</hi> is alſo moſt expreſſe &amp; cleere; For <hi>when the Donatists</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Catholickes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat dici tertiae.</note> 
                  <hi>as affirming</hi> that there were two Churches; one vpon earth, which contained both the good and bad; and the other in heauen, <hi>which contained none but good:</hi> the Catholicks made them this anſwere. <hi>That they</hi> did not make two Churches, but did only diſtinguiſh the two times of the Church, ſaying that the ſame <hi>One only Church</hi> was in one ſtate
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2348:19"/>
now, and was hereafter, to be in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: that now, it had a mixture of euill men, but that hereafter, it ſhould haue none: iuſt ſo, as there are not therefore two Chriſts, becauſe once he could dye; and now he can dye no more. And thus the Catholickes refuted that ſlaunder, which the Donatiſts had layed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; expreſly ſhewing, what they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſayed; namely, that there was <hi>but One, and the ſame holy Catholicke Church.</hi> And to ſhewe more ouer by the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>S. Augustine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione Pſal. 54.</note> that the Church, in her doctrine, was to be truly <hi>One;</hi> he ſpake thus of the <hi>Donatists, who called vpon the ſame God, preached the ſame ghoſpell, ſunge the ſame Pſalmes, had the ſame Baptiſme, obſerued the ſame Eaſter, and the like; In thoſe things they were with me, yet not who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with me; in Schiſme not with me; in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie not with me; in many things with me; in a few not with me: but in regard they were not with me in a few, their being not with me in many could not helpe them.</hi> Nay <hi>S. Ireneus</hi> (whom I named before) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies,<note place="margin">Lib. 2. cap. 3.</note> not only, <hi>That it is neceſſary for a true Chriſtian</hi> Catholicke to differ in no one point of the doctrine or faith from other Chriſtans; but he muſt withall not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2348:19"/>
beleeue any thing after a different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; that is to ſay, vpon a different <hi>motiue, from that, for which it is beleeued by other Chriſtians.</hi> But this point I ſhall touch hereafter. And for the preſent it may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to haue proued the neceſſitie of moſt perfect <hi>vnity</hi> in the Church, and that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede no reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why if there be allowed any more true Churches then <hi>One,</hi> there ſhould not be admitted, as well two thouſand as two. So that now it remaynes for me, to ſhewe alſo by the iudgment of holy Scriptures, and Fathers, that out of this <hi>One</hi> Church, there is no ſaluation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>It is prooued, both by holy ſcriptures, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that out of <hi>One true Church</hi> of Chriſt our Lord no ſaluation is to be found. <hi>CHAPTER V.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce the Church of Chriſt our Lord, is ſo truely <hi>One,</hi> and but <hi>only One;</hi> it followes eaſily inough, that no ſaluation can be had out of this Church; and that euery hereſy, or ſchiſme, is ſufficient to depriue any ſoule thereof. But yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2348:20"/>
to the end that men may be wholy left without excuſe, or rather that they may be the better warned to take heede in time, of thoſe miſeries, which otherwiſe they are to feele for all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; I will ſtrengthen alſo this trueth by the authority of ſome few Scriptures and Fathers of the primitiue Church. For ſo, by degrees, it will eaſily and of it felfe appeare, that we Catholickes are not faulty in that, wherewith we are ſo much charged.</p>
               <p>The Prophet Eſay thus foretelles the quality and condicion of the then fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Church of Chriſt our Lord and what ſhall become of them, who ſerue it not.<note place="margin">Cap. 60.</note> 
                  <hi>Gens enim, &amp; regnum, quod non ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uierit tibi, peribit. That nation, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which will not ſerue thee, shall perish.</hi> And now if a whole nation and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall periſh for not ſeruing, what ſhall become of thoſe priuate miſerable people, who blaſpheme and rent it? The ſame Prophet ſayth elſe where, to the ſame purpoſe,<note place="margin">Cap. 54.</note> 
                  <hi>Omne vas &amp;c. Euery veſsell or pot, which is framed againſt the, shall not ſucceede or proue well; and thou shalt iudge euery tongue reſisting thee in iudgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We haue ſeene already in the new
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2348:20"/>
Teſtament (vpon another occaſion to prooue the <hi>vnity</hi> of the Church) that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer obeyes not this <hi>One</hi> Church, is by the order of our bleſſed Lord himſelfe, to be held for no other then a <hi>Pagan or Publican;</hi> that is to ſay for no better then a meere Idolater in his Religion, and for a moſt infamous and baſe perſon in his conuerſation. And we may ſee now fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that S. <hi>Paule, that veſſell of election,</hi> that man who had beene rapt to the third heauen, add who had in his heart ſuch a flaming fornace of Charity, as to <hi>deſire to be made Anathema for the ſaluation of his brethren,</hi> doth moſt aboundantly declare the wofull ſtate or all heretickes and ſchiſmatickes. He requires men <hi>to auoid an heretick if he reform not himſelfe, after one or two reproofes;</hi> and he names <hi>Haereticum hominem</hi> indefinitely, without ſpecifying in particular, what his hereſie may be, more or leſſe. He ſayth alſo, that <hi>an Hereticke is condemned euen by his owne iudgment.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ad Tit. 3</note> 
                  <hi>That their ſpeech is like a Cancer whiche creepes and kills; That they attend to the ſpirit of errour, and the Doctrine of diuells; That they are hyppocrites, and lyers, couetous, arrogant, and blaſphemous; That they take the apparance of piety vpon them
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2348:21"/>
but yet renounce the vertue and ſubstance he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof; That they are euer learning, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out attayning to the knowledge of truth; That as Iannes and Mambres reſiſted Moyſes ſo doe theſe alſo reſist the truth; being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in minde, and reprobates concerning the faith; but that they shall not preuaile, but their folly shalbe made manifeſt to al, as that of Iannes and Mambres was; That they haue itching eares, which they turne away from hearing the truth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Iude.</note> 
                  <hi>And S.</hi> Iude ſaith <hi>they ar du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be Beaſts, vnfruitful trees, twiſe dead, &amp; rooted vp; cloudes without water &amp; waues of a tempeſtuous ſea, which beate themſelues into the ſome of their owne confuſion; for whom, the ſtorme of of eternall darknes is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued; and that they are men who walke the way of</hi> Cain, <hi>and</hi> Baalam; <hi>and who perish in the contradiction of Core.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By all which kind of language a man may eaſily perceaue, how farre both the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paule,</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Iude</hi> alſo, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to be from ſaluation, whoe haue deuided themſelues from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church by hereſie or ſchiſme. And S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth in cleere termes, <hi>That the workes of the flesh are manifeſt;<note place="margin">Galat. cap. 5.</note> which whoſoeuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mits, shall not poſſeſſe the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God,</hi> Amongſt which he reckons
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2348:21"/>
expreſly, contentions, emnities, diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Sects &amp;c. which word <hi>Sects</hi> in Latin, is <hi>Hereſie</hi> in Greeke. Now if any one hereſie be damnable; what ſhall they be, when they come in cluſters? And if their ſoules be to be loſt, who fall into emnity and contentions, without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues hereof; what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thoſe miſerble creatures, who violate, maligne, and wound the whole myſtical body of Chriſt our Lord, which is his Church?</p>
               <p>As for the Fathers,<note place="margin">De praeſ. aduerſus haeret</note> they are as bright as day, in this point. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, <hi>that if they be heretikes, they cannot be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Christians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> is expreſſe, and large in this argument, and ſayth thus.<note place="margin">Lib. 4. Epiſt. 2. &amp; de v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Adulterari non poteſt Sponſa Christi &amp;c. The Spouſe of Christ cannot be adulterated,</hi> ſhe is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup and chaſte; ſhe knowes one houſe, &amp; purely conſernes the Chaſtity of one bed-chamber. It is ſhe who keeps vs for God; ſhe ſets them forth for his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whome ſhe hath begotten. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is ſeparated from the Church, and is ioyned to an adultres; is ſeparated alſo from thoſe promiſes, which belonge to the Church; nor ſhall he arriue to the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2348:22"/>
rewards of Chriſt, who forſake the Church of Chriſt. He is an alien, he is a prophane perſon, and he is an enemy. He can no longer haue God for his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who hath not the Church for his Mother. If a man might haue eſcapte drowning, without being in the Arck of <hi>Noe;</hi> he ſhall alſo be able to eſcape, who is out of the Church.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> He alſo ſaith thus afterwards. They cannot remaine with God, becauſe they would not continue of one minde, in the Church of God. Though their bodies ſhould be deliuered to be burnt in the fier, or that they ſhould be deuoured by wild beaſts, ſuch a death would not be a Crown of faith but a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of perfidiouſnes in them; nor would it be a glorious end of their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but a deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> following vpon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire. Such a man may be killed, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be crowned. Iuſt ſo doth he profeſſe himſelfe to be a Chriſtian, as the diuell doth often falſely affirme himſelfe to be Chriſt; according to what our Lord him ſelfe did forewarme, and tell vs thus, <hi>Many will come in my name, ſaying I am the Christ, and they shall deceaue many.</hi> But as he is not Chriſt, though he ſhall deceaue many, vnder the colour of that name;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2348:22"/>
ſo neither can that man be accompted a Chriſtian, who remaines not in his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and faith. And in another place, he alſo ſaith,<note place="margin">Quiſquis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſt lib. 4. Epiſt. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſoeuer he be, and what kinde of man ſoeuer he be; he is no Chriſtian, who is not in the Church of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like or rather the very ſame words are vſed by S. <hi>Auguſtine Serm.</hi> 181. <hi>de te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p.</hi> &amp; elſe where alſo he ſaith thus to certaine heretickes. How can you brag,<note place="margin">Symb. ad Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. c. 10. Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo vos cam &amp;c. Lib. 2. contra Gaudon. cap. 12.</note> that you hold faſt the Faith, which our Lord left to his Apoſtles? would you haue men ſo blind and deafe, as not to heare, or read the ghoſpell, where they may know what faith our Lord left to his Apoſtles concerning his Church? from which ſince you are deuided, and ſeparated, you doe no other thing, then rebell againſt the words, both of the <hi>body,</hi> and of the <hi>head;</hi> and yet, the while, you bragge, that you endure perſecution for the <hi>Sonne of man,</hi> and for the faith, which he reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended to his Apoſtles. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth the Saint put himſelfe to ſhew our of Scripture, <hi>That this is that Church of Christ, which is ſpread ouer the whole world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De vnit Eccl. Ad ipſam &amp;c.</note> The ſame holy Father ſaith alſo, <hi>No man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to ſaluation or life euerlasting who hath not Christ for his head; and no man can haue
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2348:23"/>
Christ for his head, who is not in his bodie, which is the Church,</hi> And els where hee diſcourſeth thus,<note place="margin">Epi. 152. quiſquis ab hac &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſoeuer is ſeparated from the Catholicke Church, how laudably ſoeuer he may conceaue himſelfe to liue, yet he shall not haue life; but the wrath of God remainesh vpon him, for this only crime of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeuered from the Society of Chriſt.</hi> And to conclude (for aſmuch as concernes S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> authority touching this point) let this following ſpeech of his be well pondered, whereby it will appeare that Cardinall Petron ſaid well, when he taught that the name <hi>Catholicke</hi> was, not only a name of <hi>beliefe</hi> and <hi>faith,</hi> but of <hi>Charity</hi> alſo and <hi>Communion,</hi> which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhould want, would alſo want ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, though he were not wanting in points of faith; let vs hearken to S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine who deliuers himſelfe thus; <hi>Et hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retici &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De fide &amp; Symb cap. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>both Heretickes &amp; Schiſmatickes are wont to call their congregations by the name of Churches: Heretickes violate Fayth by belieuing falſe things of God, and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes though they belieue the ſame things with vs, doe yet fly from fraternall. Charity by their wicked diuiſions; And therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the Hereticke belong to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church, becauſe he loueth not God; nor
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2348:23"/>
the Schiſmaticke, becauſe he loueth not his neighbour. For how</hi> (ſaith theſe Sainte el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where) <hi>shall the Schiſmaticke be eſteemed to be in Charity with his neighbour, who is out of Charity or Communion with the whole body of Christ, which is his Church.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt ad Dam.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> writing to Pope <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus,</hi> ſaith (not only of the <hi>Catholicke Church indifinitely,</hi> but denoting that to be the <hi>Romane) that that Church is the Arke, out of which whoſoeuer liueth, shalbe drowned in the deluge, and that that Church is the houſe, out of which whoſoeuer should eate the lambe, were a prophane perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lactantius alſo ſayth thus;<note place="margin">Lib. 4. cap. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Sola Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Catholica est, &amp;c. It is the Catholicke Church alone, which preſerues the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God, this is the fountaine of truth, this the houſe of faith, this the Temple of God; if any man either enter not into it, or depart out of it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>he shall be depriued of the hope of ſaluation, and eternall life. No man muſt flatter himſelfe with an obstinate kind of contention for the questions here, about ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and life, which if it be not watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diligently prouided for, it will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct and loſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint Fulgentius hath this dreadfull ſaying, wherewith I will conclude this
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2348:24"/>
point. <hi>Firmiſsimè tene &amp;c. be moſt firmely perſuaded</hi> and haue not doubt at all but that euery <hi>Hereticke</hi> or <hi>Schiſmaticke,</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt, if withall he be not a member of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church</hi> can by no meanes be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, how great Almes ſoeuer he ſhall giue, yea and though he ſhould ſhed his bloode, for the name of Chriſt; For ſo long as the ſinne either of <hi>Hereſie</hi> or <hi>Schiſme</hi> (which drawes men downe to death) ſhall remaine in any man; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Baptiſme, nor Almes, nor death en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured for the name of Chriſt, can be of any benefit towards his ſaluation, who houlds not faſt the vnity of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church. And now by this we ſee what the holy Scriptures, and what the Fathers of the moſt primitiue time affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me concerning the vnſaueableneſſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, who is not a member of that Church, which formerly hath beene ſo cleerely proued to be but <hi>One;</hi> Nor will I ſo much diſtruſt either the attentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my reader as to thinke that I neede preſſe this point any further. Soe that now in the next place it will only remaine to be conſidered and reſolued;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2348:24"/>
whether or no, both the Catholickes &amp; the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be truly ſaid to be parts &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of this <hi>One</hi> and the ſelfe ſame Church? for if they can not, the caſe in queſtion is already iudged, and there will be no colour of reaſon, why either of vs ſhould hereafter be charged with want of Charity for affirming, that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not ſaueable without repentance of his Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER VI.</hi> That both Catholickes and Proteſtants can not poſsibly be accounted to be of one and the ſame Religion, Fayth and Church.</head>
               <p>HItherto I haue inſiſted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of this maine diſcourſe: wherein I vndertooke to ſhew (and doe conceaue my ſelfe to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyed with my word) that there is but one true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; one true Church; out of which there is no ſaluation.</p>
               <p>It will now remaine that I prooue the ſecond part of my vndertaking, which is that both the Catholickes &amp; Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, can by noe meanes account themſelues to be profeſſours of that one true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and obedient Children to that one
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2348:25"/>
true Church; whichſoeuer be that true Church, by the addreſſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of men may hope to ſaue their ſoules. For cleare demonſtration whereof it will be fit, in the firſt place to ſhew, what that is, which makes a diuerſity in Religion; and without which men may ſtill be of the ſame Religlon, though there be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of opinion betweene them.</p>
               <p>The very name of a Chriſtian Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereby Almighty God is to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped, implyes a doctrine which muſt be beleiued, Sacraments which muſt be receaued, diſcipline which muſt be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, &amp; Prelates or Gouernours which muſt be obeyed: &amp; therefore that which make a Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be entire, is the beliefe of the ſame doctrine, and the participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſame Sacraments, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the ſame diſcipline and Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or Gouernours, ſo farre as men doe not obſtinately reiect any part thereof, or refuſe to ſubmit thereunto. Whoſoeuer doth this, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formes his interiour, by way of beliefe, to the ſame doctrine and Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and his exteriour, by way of obedience, to the ſayd Prelates and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, may iuſtly be held to be one of the ſame Religion: and whoſoeuer refuſeth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2348:25"/>
to do this, fayles of that.</p>
               <p>But ſo alſo, on the other ſide, whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the Church hath not decided, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and commaunded a doctrine to be belieued by her children, and hath not enioyned ſuch a part of diſcipline to be embraced, a man (ſo that he commit no ſcandall in the manner of it) may varie both in the one and in the other, from other men, and may thinke and do, as he ſees cauſe; without offending the vnity of Church, or incurring thereby the crime either of hereſie or ſchiſme, as I ſhall ſhew more at large afterwards vpon an other occaſion. It muſt therefore be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered <hi>whether Catholicks and Proteſtants be of one Church or not;</hi> or rather it is to be ſeene: for indeed in this caſe men haue not ſo much neede of their wits, as of their eyes, for the reſoluing of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. But yet ſtill to the end, that euen the weakeſt ſtomackes may be made ſtrong inough to digeſt that morſell which is coming toward it, I will ſhew by ſeuerall arguments that we are farre from all poſſibility of paſſing for profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of the ſame Religion, &amp; for mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame Church, ſo longe as we continue as we are.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:2348:26"/>For who perceaues not at the firſt ſight, that we reſolutely differ from one another, in the prime and maine points of Chriſtian Religion? We embrace not all the ſame <hi>Scriptures;</hi> we differ about no fewer then <hi>fiue Sacraments</hi> of ſeauen, which Catholickes belieue with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, and they reiect withall conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt. Yea and euen concerning thoſe two, in the receiuing whereof we both agree, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely <hi>the Sacrament Baptiſme</hi> &amp; of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> there are ſo many differences and debates amongſt vs about the neceſſity of of the one, and the reall preſence of our Lord in the other; that vpon the matter we can be thought but to agree in words.</p>
               <p>We differ about the authority of <hi>all traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnwritte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> which is the very fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our beliefe of the <hi>holy Scripture</hi> it ſelfe; and conſequently, of all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther greateſt points. We differ about <hi>the Primacie of S. Peter,</hi> and his ſucceſſours; yea and about <hi>the infallibility of generall Councells;</hi> and ſo therefore about <hi>the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme iudge on earth of all our controuerſies in</hi> Religion. We differ, about <hi>the iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſoules,</hi> and the value which the death and grace of Chriſt our Lord hath imparted to <hi>the workes</hi> of the children of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2348:26"/>
God. We differ in a world of particulars, about <hi>the article of holy Catholicke Church,</hi> and namely whether it muſt alwayes be viſible or noe euen, to the eyes of men; and whether it muſt alwayes be free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> errour and fallibility. We differ about the <hi>Communion of Saincts,</hi> &amp; whether we may either <hi>pray for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who are in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who are in heauen.</hi> And we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not only about theſe, and many other moſt importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t points, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who ar ready to relinquiſh their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, if they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded: but we ar on both ſides reſolued to perſiſt; though both the Catholicke Church in her counſells, and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in their ſeuerall <hi>Confeſsions,</hi> haue declared that their owne opinions are true, and the contrary falſe: and though we on the one ſide haue caſt excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication vpon the new deniers of thoſe doctrines of ours, which we haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt our Lord, &amp; his Apoſtles; and they on the other, haue filled their parts of the world, which ſcurrill &amp; blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous inuectiues againſt thoſe ſayd Doctrines of ours; and haue taken vpon themſelues to be the reformers of the Church, though without either ordinary miſſion, or miracles; and to be true pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhers
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2348:27"/>
of the ghoſpell, and euen the very illuminatours of the world.</p>
               <p>And now therefore let that be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered once for all, which hath formerly ben ſhewed, about the ſtile of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture &amp; Fathers, which ſpeake thoſe ſaid things of <hi>Hereſies and Hereticks,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpecifying in particular, what they are. And let it alſo be called to minde, what <hi>Catalogues</hi> the Fathers of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, haue made of <hi>hereſies,</hi> whereof many (abſtracting fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pride and diſobedience, which thereby is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the Church) are neither of ſo great importance in themſelues, or at leaſt not great at all, in reſpect of thoſe many moſt important Articles, which ar mutually affirmed or denied betwene the Proteſtants and vs. For what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported it all, that ſome were ſo fooliſh, as to hold al men bound by Scripture to put of their ſhoes when they prayed: &amp; yet <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> cited them for heretickes in his Catalogue. But the pride where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they preſumed to abuſe Scripture, and to impoſe ſuch a fond law vpon me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences &amp; a reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to leaue it, when they were commaunded by the Church, was that which made it <hi>hereſy</hi> in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2348:27"/>
them. Or what Article of the Creede? or what book of Scripture? or what ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Church, did the <hi>Quartodecimani</hi> deny; or what errour did they introduce, but only the celebrating of Eaſter at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other time, then was ordained by the Church? and yet for this doth S. <hi>Austin</hi> inroll them in the rancke of heretickes. &amp; the ſame I might exemplifie in many other particulars.</p>
               <p>Preſumption and pride, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by chooſing, &amp; obſtinatly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of any doctrine or diſcipline, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the iudgment and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Catholicke Church; and by refuſing to ſubmit therein to the ſame Church; is that wherein the very life &amp; ſpirit, of <hi>Schiſme and Hereſie</hi> doth conſiſt.</p>
               <p>And the queſtion is not here, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the point, vpon which the <hi>Schiſme</hi> or <hi>hereſie</hi> is grounded, be in it ſelfe of ſo great importance yea or no? but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be in the hearte of any priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te man or men, ſuch a diabolicall degree of obſtinacy and pride, as to preferre their owne ſence and Iudgment, in things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the faith and worſhip of our Lord God, before the reſolution and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of his holy Catholicke Church,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2348:28"/>
which is his ſpouſe, his kingdome, his houſe, his Sanctuary and his citty, which was made the treaſure houſe of grace, the foundation and pillar of truth, the depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitary of the holy Ghoſt, and the heire of moſt faithfull and firme promiſes, that <hi>euen the gates and power of Hell it ſelfe should neuer be able to preuaile againſt it.</hi> And now I ſay, if there be found ſuch a ſinne as this in the ſoule of man, as to preferre his owne poore dictamens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the decrees of this Church, it is ſo very enormous, ſo barbarous, ſo wholy out of the way of al Religion, of reaſon, of nature, and euen of common ſence; &amp; it ſauours of ſuch a ſpirituall and infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall preſumption (ſo much the more cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially to be firſt lamented, and then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, becauſe it is cloaked vnder the collour <hi>of the ghoſpell, and Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and I know not what of that kind) that really it can deſerue no other place or degree of puniſhment, then Hell it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>And now that all this is true; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that hereſie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtes not in the material beliefe of a falſe doctrine (for the contrary thereof perhaps, was not ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to be belieued) but in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2348:28"/>
to the Church, after it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, that famous exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> and the <hi>Donatistes</hi> may ſerue for prooffe. For <hi>S. Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> was of the firſt who fel vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the doctrine <hi>of rebaptization of ſuch as had beene baptized by Hereticks;</hi> and the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists</hi> afterward ſucceeded in the ſame. But in <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> it was but errour, becauſe the Church of his time, had not abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely condemned it; but growing after to condemned, in the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> time; it was <hi>Hereſie</hi> in them not to forſake it. Which drew <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis</hi> to make this exclamation, <hi>O admirable change of things! the authours of an opinion are held Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks; and the followers of the ſelfe ſame, are iudged hereticks.</hi> And <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> himſelfe declares the ſame in ſubſtance, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a like occaſion concerning others. For when one inquired of him, what that errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doctrine was, which <hi>Nouatianus</hi> the ſchiſmatick had taught; his anſwere to his friend was directly this. <hi>Thou muſt know that we should not be curious what that doctrine is which he teaches, ſince he is out of the Church;</hi> teachinge clearly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that not the quality of the doctrine, but the pride of the man, is that which makes the hereticke.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:2348:29"/>And in deede if this were not the rule, whereby <hi>hereſies</hi> and <hi>ſchiſmes</hi> muſt be knowne, it were impoſſible to conclude what were an <hi>hereſie</hi> or a <hi>ſchiſme;</hi> and ſo alſo there ſhould fall out to be no here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in effect at all, which might not be compatible with ſaluation. Now this opinion, is not only contrary to the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of holy Scriptures and Fathers, and to the beliefe and practiſe of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church of all ages; but euen of the Proteſtants themſelues, who condemne not only vs, but one an another alſo as is abundantly ſhewed the Authour of the Proteſtants Apologie, &amp;c. for the Roman Church and eſpecially in the place cited in the Margine;<note place="margin">fol. 408.</note> where he ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Luther expreſly ſaying thus. <hi>We ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly cenſure the Zuinglians, and all the Sacramentaries, for hereticks, and as alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from the Church of God.</hi> And I <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test before God and the world, that I agree not with them, nor euer will: but will haue my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d cleare from the blood of thoſe sheepe, which theſe hereticks driue from Christ, deceaue and kill.</hi> And againe, in the ſame place, <hi>Curſed be the Charity, and concord of Sacramentaries for euer, and euer, to all eternity.</hi> And a litle before his death, he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2348:29"/>
proteſteth ſaying: <hi>I hauing now one of my feete in the graue, will carry this teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and glory, to the tribunall of God; That I will with all my heart condemne and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew Carolostadius, Zuinglius, Oecolampa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, &amp; their diſciples; nor will haue fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity with any of them neither by letter, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, words, nor deedes, accordingly as the Lord hath commaunded:</hi> Thus he ſayth with very much more to the ſame effect. And to make this yet more euident by the like teſtimonyes of the <hi>Zuinglians,</hi> &amp; <hi>Caluinists: the Tigurine</hi> Diuines ſay thus; <hi>Nos, condemnatam &amp; execrabilem vocat ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam &amp;c. Luther calls vs a damnable and execrable ſect; but let him looke, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare not himſelfe an Archheretick; ſince he will not nor cannot haue any ſociety with thoſe that confeſſe Christ. But how maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly doth Luther here bewray himſelfe with his diuells; what filthy words doth he vſes? &amp; ſuch as are replenished with all the diuells in helle For he ſayth that the diuell dwelleth both now and euer, in the Zuinglians; and that they haue a blaſphemous brest inſatha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, perſathanized, and ſuperſathanized; and that they haue beſides, a most vaine mouth, ouer which Sathan beareth rule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infuſed, perfuſed and transfuſed into the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2348:30"/>
ſame. Did euer man heare ſuch ſpeeches paſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a furious diuell himſelfe?</hi> In ſo much as <hi>Zuinglius</hi> ſayth of him, <hi>Behould how Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth endeauour wholly to poſseſſe this man.</hi> And <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> alſo forewarnes <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, leaſt being puffed vp by arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy &amp; pride he be ſeduced by Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Wherunto might be added ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry other like teſtimonies. This contention betweene Luther and his followers on the one party, and the Zuinglians or Caluiniſts on the other, is yet further teſtified, not only by the almoſt infinite writings of on againſt an other yet dayly encreaſing; but alſo by the knowne mutuall proſcription or ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ech other, from their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall territories or dominions. So farre were they from reputing one another for members of one and the ſame Church. Thus farre goe the words of the ſayd A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poligie, where you ſhall finde the places both of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius</hi> and <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lampadius,</hi> and the <hi>Tigurine</hi> diuines, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly cited.</p>
               <p>Heare alſo further, what <hi>Nicolaus Gallus</hi> ſaith (who was an eminent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter at Ratisbone) of the difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Proteſtants themſelues. <hi>Non ſunt leues &amp;c,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In The ſib. &amp; Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſ.</note> 
                  <hi>The diſsentions which are
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2348:30"/>
amongst vs, be not light, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning light matters; but about the greatest Articles of of Christian Doctrine; of the law, and the ghoſpell; of iuſtification and good workes; of the Sacraments, and vſe of ceremonies.</hi> Heare alſo what <hi>Conradus Schluſſenbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> another famous Lutheran Proteſtant ſayth, in the very Title of his booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Caluiniſts, <hi>Theologiae Caluini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticae libri tres &amp;c. Three bookes concerning Caluinia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuinity, wherein it is shewed as in a Table to the eye, out of two hundred &amp; thre and twenty publicke writers of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries (with particular ſetting downe the pages, the words, &amp; the names of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours) that the ſaid Sacramentaries haue no true belief of almost any Article of Christian Faith.</hi> This booke was printed at Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford in the yeare 1594. Reade alſo but the very <hi>Title</hi> of two of <hi>Grauerus</hi> his bookes (who was a famous profeſſour of Lutheraniſme; the one is this; <hi>Abſurda abſurdoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abſurdiſsima, Caluinistica abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da. The abſourd &amp; moſt abſourd doctrines &amp; Caluin &amp;c.</hi> and the other, <hi>Bellum Ioannis Caluini &amp; Ieſu Christi,</hi> printed 1598. <hi>The warre of Iohn Caluin against Ieſus Christ.</hi> And laſtly, doe but read this Title of book writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by <hi>Aegidius Hunnius,</hi> who
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2348:31"/>
was a moſt famous Lutheran, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded next to <hi>Luther</hi> himſelfe in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing his Chaire at Wittenberge. The Title is this <hi>Aegidij Hunnij Caluinus Iudai. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ans id eſt, &amp;c.</hi> Caluin playing the Iew; that is to ſay, A diſcouery made by <hi>Aegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Hunnius,</hi> of the Iewiſh <hi>Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and corruptions, whereby</hi> Iohn Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath not bene afrayde, to corrupt (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a detestable ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner) moſt illuſtrious places, and teſtimonies of holy Scripture concerning the glorious Trinity, the Deity of Chriſt, &amp; of the holy Ghost; and eſpecially of predictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Prophets touching the coming of the Meſsias, his Natiuity, Paſsion, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, &amp; ſitting at the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God. Printed at Wittenberge in the yeare</hi> 1592.</p>
               <p>I forbeare both to preſſe this euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; I will no further ſeeke to prooue by way of Authority, that both Catholicks and Proteſtants are not ſauable, as not being to be accounted, to be of one and the ſame Church and Religion, no not yet euen the Lutherans and Caluiniſts. For in a word, that reaſon ſtrikes euen at the roote, which is drawen from the nature &amp; propriety of faith it ſelfe. And euen that alone, if it be well conſidered, will vnanſwerably conuince, not only
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2348:31"/>
that they are of differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t faith &amp; Church, who differ in ſo many Articles of ſo great moment, as theſe wherein we profeſſe one ſelues to diſagree: but that they alſo, who differ in any one ſingle point, which is propounded and commanded by the Catholicke Church: yea and more ouer, that they who differ not in any points at all, if yet they aſſent not, vpon the only true infallible ground, which is (as hath bene ſaid) the reuelation of Almighty God, and the Propoſition and Direction of the ſaid Catholicke Churh; not only haue the ſelfe ſame faith, with that Church; but that they haue no ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and true faith at all, euen of thoſe other doctrines, which they moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thinke themſelues to imbrace; and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently that it is wholly impoſſible for them to be ſaued, if they dye impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent.</p>
               <p>The reaſon whereof is excellently deliuered by <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> and many other diuines who vnaunſwerably prooue, that whoſoeuer belieues not the whole corps of Chriſtian Doctrine, hath no true <hi>ſupernaturall faith</hi> at all, and doth not righly belieue any one Article thereof. He may haue a kinde of <hi>materiall fayth,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:2348:32"/>
concerning thoſe articles, to which he giues aſſent, but not a certaine and true and ſupernaturall faith, vnles he belieue them vpon the right grounde thereof; which is, <hi>The ſpeech, or reuelation of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, propounded and commaunded to belieued by the Catholicke Church.</hi> For example, if I ſhould belieue, that Chriſt our Lord dyed for the ſins of the world, either becauſe I had only read it in ſome learned booke; or in regard that I had ben told ſo by ſome friend, whom I much eſteemed and loued; or elſe becauſe I thought it likely, in reſpect of ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity thereof to other things; or finally vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other humane and fallible mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue whatſoeuer; it is cleare that I could haue no ſupernaturall faith at all, euen concerning that one ſingle article of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke doctrine. And the ſame is to be ſaid of the reſt, whether they be many or few, great or ſmalle. And the vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted reaſon hereof is, becauſe I giue not my firme aſſent to it vpon the only true infallible motiue, which is the reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, &amp; the propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Church. For whatſoeuer is leſſe then this, cannot erect and qualifie an act of <hi>ſupernaturall faith,</hi> with muſt be abſolutely vndoubted
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2348:32"/>
and certaine; and otherwiſe it is noe true faith at all, but opinion and perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or humane beliefe. He therfore with belieues not euery particular Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Catholicke Doctrine, which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed and propounded by Almightie God and his Church, doth no aſſent eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to any one of them, which he belieues, vpon the ſayd only true and infallible motiue. For if he did, he would as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, or rather indeede could not chooſe, but as willingly belieue all the reſt, ſince they all come recomended to him by the ſame Authority. And now if there be truth in this, which indeed can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be called into any queſtion, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes and Proteſtants are farre inough from being of one faith and Church; ſince it is demonſtrated that beſides the maine differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, which runne betweene vs, either they or we haue not really any true and ſupernaturall faith at all of any one doctrine of the Church, wherein yet we ſeeme to conſent together. For as <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Mores</hi> who belieue in <hi>God the Father,</hi> haue yet no true ſupernaturall faith euen of that one ſingle Article, nor the <hi>Iewes</hi> of any thing contained euen in the <hi>old Teſtament;</hi> ſo neither hath any <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke,</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:2348:33"/>
of any thing contained either, in the <hi>old or new;</hi> ſince they all reſemble one another in this, that whatſoeuer they belieue, it is not done vpon that motiue, which only can make an act of true and ſupernaturall faith.</p>
               <p>And thus it ſhall ſuffice me to haue proued (according to the maine proiect of this diſcourſe) that <hi>there is but one true faith, which is the foundation of the only one true Religion, which is exerciſed in one only true Church,</hi> wherewith Chriſtians are bound to communicate; and that out of this Church, there is no ſaluation to be found; and laſtly that both Catholicks and Proteſtants can by no meanes be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for members of one and the ſame true Church of Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>But Proteſtants <hi>(Qui nolunt intelligere vt bene agant)</hi> though their reaſon tell them that al this is true, do yet find their Religion to be ſo vnſoundly built, that they can hardly be drawne to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment thereof. And therefore they are wont to ſay, that ſuch <hi>vnity of faith,</hi> as this whereof we haue ſpoken, is a kind of impracticable thing in this life; that the holy Scripture ſpeaking thereof is not to be vnderſtood in ſuch a rigid
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2348:33"/>
ſenſe; that the Fathers of the primitiue Church, were too preciſe that way; that their diſcourſe of this kind was metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall; and that ſaluation is no ſo hard to be obtained; but that there is roome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough in heauen for both Religions. And finally they obiect, that there is no ſuch exact <hi>vnity</hi> as I haue her deſcribed, euen amongſt vs Catholickes; and that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues maintaine a ſufficiency of vnity in faith, both with the Fathers of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, and with their owne fellow brethren the Lutheranes; yea &amp; ſome moreouer will be ſo courteous, as to profeſſe that they agree, euen with vs moderne Papiſts, in all <hi>Fundamentall points of faith.</hi> But I will conſider in the next chapter, both how litle reaſon they haue in what they obiect herein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs; and in what alſo they alleadge for themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:2348:34"/>
               <head>The auoiding of three obiections, which they make against vs, to diſproue our vnitie in faith amongst our ſelues; and of a fourth allegation, whereby they would shew that they hold as much <hi>vnity</hi> both with the Lutherans, and euen with vs Catholickes at this day, as they are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to maintaine. <hi>CHAPTER VII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THey firſt ſtriue to impeach our <hi>vnity</hi> in faith, by obiecting that variety of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in ſome points which they find by our books, to be amongſt vs; whereby they would inferre, that there is alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs a diuerſity of beliefe and faith; and there is nothing more vſuall with them then this diſcourſe. But the anſwere is ſhortly and clerely this. That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they find our Doctours to be of a contrary opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they ſhall alſo find thoſe points in queſtion, not be haue bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by the Church; but left at liberty to be debated and diſputed, as men ſee cauſe. Such are a world of difficultyes betweene the <hi>Thomiſts</hi> and <hi>Scotiſts; de au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xilijs,</hi> betwene the <hi>Dominicans</hi> and the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2348:34"/>
                  <hi>Ieſuites;</hi> wherein either ſide defendes that which they take to be the truth, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the contrary opinion, by all the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that occure. And both ſides, the while, are reſolued, &amp; ready to ſubmit, to the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Church whenſoeuer it ſhall be declared; ſo <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiuating their vnderstanding to the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of faith, as the Apostle exhorts.</hi> And in the meane time, <hi>they preſerue the ſpirit of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, in the bond of peace.</hi> If our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries could ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w that they erected <hi>Altare contra altare,</hi> or that they were reſolued not to obey to the definition of the Church, when it were declared, they ſhould haue reaſon on their ſide: but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they are either very ignorant, or els full of malice, who make this obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And let them either ſhew, what Ieſuite and Dominican breakes commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with on another, or els betake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to ſome better prooffes.</p>
               <p>The next obiection is yet more ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide then the former; and I wonder how <hi>Caluins</hi> rage againſt the Church could put him ſo farre out of his wits, as that he would euer take it into his mouth. For it is he, who (being pricked by our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their want of vnity towards their
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2348:35"/>
fellow brethren) thinkes to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ort it backe vpon vs, by ſaying that we are not in caſe, to obiect any ſuch thing againſt them; foraſmuch as that forſooth, we haue as many ſects amongſt vs, as we haue ſeuerall Orders of Religious men; and then he rekons vp <hi>Benedictans, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melites, Dominicans, Franciſcans,</hi> &amp; whom els he will. Wicked man, who well knewe, that no one of thoſe holy <hi>Orders,</hi> doth differ in any one point of doctrine from any of the reſt, &amp; are ſo farre from breaking communion with them, as that ſtill they <hi>preuent one another in all honour and good reſpects,</hi> according to the aduice of the <hi>Bleſſed Apoſtle;</hi> and much more do they exhibite all poſſible reuerence and obedience to the ſame Church, and the Prelates thereof. The difference which indeede raignes amongſt them, is who ſhal ſtrip themſelues ſooneſt of all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incombrance, and ſo fly the faſter to heauen. They haue ſeuerall <hi>Rules</hi> indeed which were framed by their ſeuerall <hi>Founders,</hi> thoſe men of God; whereby they might the better direct their courſe to this iourneyes end, according to thoſe ſeuerall ſpirits which our Lord imparts to ſeueral perſons. For though any man
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2348:35"/>
may be good in any lawfull ſtate of life, but eſpecially in ſome holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Religion; yet becauſe men are not only of ſeuerall conſtitutions in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but of as ſeuerall diſpoſitions alſo in minde; and that ſome are apter for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, others for a more actiue life; ſome for corporall auſterities, others for mentall reflections and mortifications; ſome for catechiſing, preaching and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, others for ſilence and recollectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; <hi>Vt omnis ſpiritus laudent Dominum,</hi> it was moſt agreable to the ſweete prouidence of Almighty God, to inſpire his emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeruants with ſeuerall ſpirits, who might erect ſeuerall Orders at ſeuerall times, which ſeuerall natures might affect, and ſo apply themſelues to God, both more cheerfully &amp; more fruitfully therein; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if they conſerue that ſpirit, with which the Order was firſt indued. And as wel &amp; wiſely might <hi>Caluin</hi> haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſt a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Religion amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues becauſe ſome men weare gownes &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers cloakes; as to haue argued a diſunio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt our Religious men, becauſe of their differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in habit or diet, either fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other <hi>Orders,</hi> or elſe from ſecular people.</p>
               <p>I heare them alſo make a third ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2348:36"/>
againſt our <hi>vnity</hi> in points of faith; in regard of the difference betweene our learned and vnlearned men; for in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence thereof they ſay, that ſome one of vs belieues incomparably more, then an other. For the clearing of this point I will open a certaine diſtinction, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect whereof they are wont to lay to our chardge as a crime: but if they lend me a litle patience, the ſame will ſerue them for a light, to let them ſee that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues are out of the way.</p>
               <p>This diſtinction, is of <hi>Explicite</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite faith.</hi> A man is ſayd to haue <hi>Explicite faith</hi> of any Article or doctrine, when he hath heard it particularly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him, and hath ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar knowledge thereof, and giues parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular aſſent thereunto. But as for <hi>Implicite faith</hi> of any Article or doctrine, a man is then ſayd to haue it, when he belieues that concerning it, which the Church teaches them <hi>explicitly,</hi> who are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereof; although for his owne part, he haue not perhaps ſo much as heard of it in particular; or if he did, he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got it; or if he remember it, he hath not capacity inough to apprehend, or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. But howſoeuer (as I ſayd) he is
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2348:36"/>
reſolued to belieue both of that and all things elſe, as the Church teaches; &amp; wil giue an <hi>Explicite conſent</hi> to it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhal be informed hereof, &amp; be made ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to vnderſtand it; &amp; hath this firme reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he will neuer hold he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary either of that, or of any other thing, which they Church ſhal require him to belieue.</p>
               <p>This I ſay is our doctrine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Explicite</hi> and <hi>Implicite faith,</hi> and I dare confidently affirme, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer conſiders the ſame indifferently, and with a reſolution to receaue ſatisfaction if there be cauſe, and not to be ſtill ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilling, whether there becauſe or noe; will confeſſe, that not only the doctrine of <hi>Explicite</hi> and <hi>Implicite faith,</hi> doth not only not impeach our <hi>vnity</hi> in beliefe, in regard that ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> belieue ſome things more <hi>Explicitely,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen others do; but that, if it were poſſible to abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſh this doctrine (which indeed it is impoſſible to do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is rather deliuered vs by the voice of nature it ſelfe, which hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a different capacity in the mindes of men) it would be wholly impoſſible to maintaine any Church in any <hi>vnity</hi> of faith at all. For example; will any man amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them be ſo abſurd, as to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaue
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2348:37"/>
that any plough man, or Trades man, or ſilly Woman, doth belieue the ſame things <hi>Explicitely,</hi> concerning <hi>Originall ſinne,</hi> or the relation which runnes <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene free will and grace,</hi> and a hundred other queſtions of this nature, which may be <hi>Explicitly</hi> belieued by ſome prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Doctour of diuinity amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them, who haue particular ſtudied theſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions? And if they confeſſe they cannot, will they be content that we ſhall inferre thereby, that there is no <hi>vnity of faith</hi> maintained amongſt them? Infallibly they will not: and therefore it is but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they meaſure, as they would be meaſured to; and that they acknowledge that if diſſenſion in point of faith, could depend vpon the <hi>Expliciteneſse, or Impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeneſſe</hi> of a mans belieuing ſeuerall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, there would be, in effect, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeuerall faithes, amongſt vnlearned Chriſtians, as there are ſeuerall capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. For as much as we can hardly finde, two ſuch men, whereof the one belieues iuſt as much <hi>Explicitely</hi> and no more, then the other doth; becauſe the notice, and the attention, and the capacity, and the memory, and the profeſſion, is euer in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect more or leſſe in one, then in another,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2348:37"/>
and according to the more or leſſe of theſe circumſtance, will the Articles <hi>Explicitely</hi> beleiued be either more or leſſe. The truth concerning this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar holds not only in the Catholicke Church, but in all congregations which profeſſe any Religion whatſoeuer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of ſeuerall Articles &amp; parts. They who are learned and haue eminent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments of nature, and apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with particular induſtry, muſt euer belieue <hi>Explicitely</hi> more points of their Religion, whatſoeuer it be; and thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who are of contraries qualities, muſt belieue <hi>Explicitely</hi> fewer points. And this is alſo clear, that the more points of any Religion, which a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieues <hi>Explicitely,</hi> the fewer doth the leaue himſelfe to belieue <hi>Implicitely;</hi> and ſo on the contrary ſide, the more he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieues <hi>Implicitely,</hi> he reaches ſo much the fewer with an <hi>Explicite faith.</hi> He may &amp; muſt belieue all the Articles, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of his Religion, with a true, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, moſt certaine and ſupernatural faith; but that he ſhould belieue them all with an <hi>Explicite faith,</hi> is neither neceſſary, nor poſſible. But by belieuing as much as he can with an <hi>Explicite faith,</hi> and what
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2348:38"/>
he can not, with an <hi>Implicite;</hi> a Cardinal Bellarmine, and a Collier; nay the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt Catholicke woman in the whole world, and the moſt glorious Mother of God, if ſhe liued ſtill on earth, ſhould be abſolutely &amp; fully of the ſelfe ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; faith wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h one another. So that the ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd of our aduerſaries prooues a buckler to vs; and that obiection which they make to diſproue our <hi>vnity in faith,</hi> (vnder which they would both ſhelter their weaknes, when we iuſtly obiect their departure from the Church againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; alſo authorize their malice, when they haue a minde to caſt the ſcandall of affected ignorance vpon vs) prooues a foundation to vs of that truth, which ſhewes how our vnity is made perfect.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the three obiections, which Proteſtants are wont to make againſt our vnity in point of faith. And now there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines an allegation or argumt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they procure to defend themſelues againſt our obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they want vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty amongſt themſelues. For in vertue hereof they affirme, that they ought not to be held in diſunion, either with the Fathers of the primitiue Church, or which the Lutherans or ſuch other fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2348:38"/>
ghoſpellers of theirs at this day, or indeed euen with vs Catholickes; if things, as they ſay, may be conſidered with moderation: and all this they take to be ſecured, by diſtinguiſhing points of faith, <hi>into Fundamentall</hi> and <hi>not Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall;</hi> and then by ſaying that they agree both with the Fathers, and Lutheranes, and ſometimes (of their curteſie) euen with vs, in all <hi>fundamentall points of faith,</hi> and that they differ but in points <hi>not fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall.</hi> It is a matter of great mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that this particular conceit be carefully ſifted and diſcouered; and therefore I wil aske leaue that the next Chapter may be ſpent about it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>That Protestants haue no reaſon in alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diſtinction of <hi>fundamentall, &amp; not fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall points or faith;</hi> as intending to prooue thereby, that they are in <hi>vnity</hi> with the Fathers of the Primitiue Church, of their fellow Brethren the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, yea and ſome times with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes at this day. <hi>CHAPTER VIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BOth <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> &amp; their next diſciples, yea and many Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2348:39"/>
alſo of theſe dayes, haue familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their ſermons, and no leſſe freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their bookes, taken liberty, with euery pennefull of incke to daſh as it were damnation into our eyes; and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to affirme, that they departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Communion of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> becauſe forſooth they <hi>found it to be the ſeate of Antichriſt, the Synagogue of Satan, the very Center of ſuperſtition and Idolatry;</hi> and finally, that bloody tyrant, which exerciſed all immaginable cruelty againſt the Saints of God for many ages, and which poiſoned the world with falſe &amp; prophanes doctrines, of extreme diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour vnto Almighty God. And indeede with what collour could certaine ſingle, baſe, and filthie men haue preſumed to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the viſible Catholicke Church of Chriſt our Lord, and to erect their conuenticles as they did, if they had not ar leaſt profeſſed, that they could not finde ſaluation there? For if they had ſaid that they might haue found it there, they could not ſo much as haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to iuſtifie their departure from thence. But yet neuertheleſſe now that many moderne Proteſtants haue beene taught by time, that the ſtraits, into which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2348:39"/>
they fall, are great by proteſting againſt our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that kind, they haue been content now and then, to deſire better quarter at our hands; and to affirme that the differences betweene them and vs, concerne not the fundamentall points of faith, but only ſuch as are not funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall; that therefore for their parts, they hold we may be ſaued, if we leade good liues in our Religion: and that they deſire the like atteſtation of vs for them; and thas it is but tyranny and cruelty in the Catholicke Romane Church, which keepes from allowing it; ſince vpon the matter, the Religions of vs both are the ſame, &amp; the Churches in effect the ſame. And this is that, which lightens, as they thinke, our chardge of them; and ſtill keepes theirs heauy vpon vs, as being vncharitable in not allowing them ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
               <p>This diſcourſe of theirs, and their ſtanding ſo much vpon fundamentall points of faith, in the ſenſe which they vſe, is a mere Chimera: but it is frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them, through a high kind of craft. For though it be moſt true, that ſome doctrines are in themſelues of farre more importance, then ſome others; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2348:40"/>
the knowledge thereof, may be neceſſary for the performance of ſome duty which is required at our hands; or elſe becauſe they may containe the very heads and firſt grounds of Chriſtianity, more then others doe; and therefore do exact a more explicite beliefe at the hands of Chriſtians, and conſequently may be accounted in ſome reſpects more fundamentall: yet ſo, on the other ſide, there is no doctrine at all concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the beliefe whereof is not fundamentall to my ſaluation, if the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church, which is the ſpouſe of Chriſt our Lord, propound and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande me to belieue it. For there is no errour in faith, which may not be made damnable by the manner of holding it, when it is done ſo obſtinately, as that in defence thereof, a man denies the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Catholicke Church.</p>
               <p>This is vnanſwereably prooued by the meere Catalogues of hereſies, which haue been made by ſeuerall Fathers of the primitiue Church, and eſpecially by <hi>S. Austin,</hi> in his treatiſe <hi>ad Quod vult Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> which I haue toucht before, and which I earneſtly exhort my reader to peruſe at large. For therein he noteth diuerſe,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2348:40"/>
which conſiſt but of ſingle erroneous doctrines, and they of litle importance in themſelues, as was declared in a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer chapter. But yet for as much as they were obſtinately imbraced, they were there declared to be ſo fundamentall, as that he was noe Chriſtian Catholicke, who belieued any one of them; yea or who ſhould afterward belieue any other, which might chaunce to be condemned by the Catholicke Church.</p>
               <p>Looke backe vpon the example of <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> in the 6. chapter: for there you will find, that the ſelfe ſame doctrine of Rebaptization, which was not funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall to him, in regard that the Church had not then defined it; the ſame, I ſay, was fundamentall afterward to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſtes and made them Heretickes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then it was defined, and yet ſtill maintained by them. Looke backe to ſee in the ſame place, what the nature of true faith is: which is not only, that it be abſolutely entire in itſelfe; but that the meanes of propounding the Articles thereof be alſo both certaine, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely infallible: or elſe there will be no faith at all. See alſo in the ſame Chapter, where the forme and ſpirit of hereſie is
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2348:41"/>
found to conſiſt in the pride and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, wherewith any doctrine or diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church is diſobeyed; and then withall caſt an eye vpon that, which you may find in the fifte Chapter of this diſcourſe, about the iudgment, which is pronounced there, both by Scriptures &amp; Fathers about the vnſaueablenes of any ſoule, which is guilty of the leaſt hereſie, or ſchiſme and ſeparation from the one and only true Church of Chriſt our Lord. For by this meanes it will appeare moſt euidently, that the diſtinction of Faith, into <hi>Fundamentall</hi> and <hi>not Fundamentall</hi> points (to the purpoſe of permitting it in a mans liberty to leaue any one of them vnbelieued, wirhout preiudice to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) is both friuolous, dangerous, and vtterly falſe: and ſo I ſhall be excuſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> growing into length by making vnneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary repetitions, which I am moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to auoid.</p>
               <p>But in the meane time, I ſhould be glad to know, of the authours of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what points of their faith, which are controuerted eitheir betweene them or vs, or betweene the Lutherans and them, are fundamentall, and which are not fundamentall? The very nature of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2348:41"/>
the words ſeeme to ſhewe; that a fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall point of faith, is ſuch an one as is moſt neceſſarily to be belieued; and that whoſoeuer belieues it not, cannot be ſaued. And that ſo alſo on the other ſide, a man may take his liberty, either to belieue as he ſees cauſe, or not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue any doctrine, which is not funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall, without incuring the ſentence of damnation. Vpon this it followes, that there is nothing in all Chriſtian Religion, which according to their groundes it imports a man more exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to learne, then what is fundamentall and what not; nor which it more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the Doctours and guides of the Proteſtant Church to make knowne to all that people, which they pretend to guide in the way of ſaluation. And yet neuertheleſſe, there is abſolutely no one thing, which hath beene ſo frequently &amp; importunately deſired, as that they would giue in, ſome exact liſt or Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of all, and the only fundamentall points of faith: and yet is there no one thing, wherein we are ſo litle ſatisfied, and which vpon the matter, they doe ſo abſolutely refuſe. And yet (as hath beene here expreſſed) if according to their
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2348:42"/>
groundes a man ſhould faile of belieue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing any one fundamental point of faith, by his not knowing (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrough their fault) that the point, which he belieued not was fundamentall, he muſt be ſure to periſh and that for euer.</p>
               <p>But the Proteſtants are wiſe inough in their owne waye, and well they know what they do, in order to their owne ends, both when they frame the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of fundamentall and not fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall points of faith; and when alſo they refuſe to giue in a Catalogue of which is which. For by making firſt the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and then by concealing the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars contained vnder the branches thereof, they ſaue themſelues harmeles amongſt ignorant people, from being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced to be of a different Communion and Religion, both from the Fathers of the primitiue Church, on the one ſide; and from their fellow ſectaries of this age, on the other. Whereby they gaine a kind of reputation with their vulgar auditours and readers, as if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a ſufficiency of vnity with both.</p>
               <p>Whereas if either they framed not the diſtinction of <hi>fundamentall</hi> at all, or elſe would clearly let men know which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2348:42"/>
points alone were <hi>fundamentall;</hi> then this would followe. That whenſoeuer we ſhould conuince them of any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular doctrine, which is denied by them, and which yet was belieued by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, they would be obliged to profeſſe, that either that point was not <hi>fundamentall,</hi> which would diſable them from rayling at vs for belieuing the ſame; or elſe that the Fathers were of a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Religion in <hi>fundamentall</hi> points from them; and that in their opinion, thoſe very Fathers could not be ſaued; which would put them to much preiudice an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way. And ſo vpon the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they would alſo either be forced to renounce the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, if they were found to differ from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>fundamentall</hi> points of faith; or elſe to avowe expreſly, that thoſe points, which they belieued differently from them, were not <hi>fundamentall,</hi> which would be of no leſſe da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; diſreputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>But now, when we vrge them (for example ſake) with the doctrine of praying to Saints, of prayer for the dead, or the like, out of the ancient Fathers; &amp; that once we bring them from denying <hi>via facti,</hi> that the Fathers taught that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2348:43"/>
doctrine, which yet they will be ſure to confeſſe as cautelouſly as they can; they then tell vs ſtreight, that thoſe Fathers were but men, and had their errours. We aske them then, if thoſe errours depriue them of ſaluation? They ſay noe; becauſe thoſe points forſooth, were not <hi>fundamentall:</hi> and thus, as hath bene ſaid, they will ſeeme to keepe a kinde of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with the Fathers. In the ſelfe ſame manner when we vrge them in the name of Lutherans, with the Reall Preſence of of the body of our Lord in the Bleſſed Sacrament of the Altar, or with their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the Epiſtle of <hi>S. Iames</hi> and diuerſe others out of the Canon of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; by their forbearing to avowe and declare that theſe points of Religion are <hi>fundamentall,</hi> they goe inuiſible to the eyes of ſimple people; and ſtill make a ſhift to ſeeme to be in vnity with the Lutherans; when yet the world knowes and we haue ſeene, that Luther himſelfe declared them directly to be heretickes.</p>
               <p>Not only doth this diſtinction of their doctrines into <hi>fundamentall</hi> and not <hi>fundamentall</hi> ſaue their credits amongſt weake me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by making them belieue that they ioyne in vnity of faith, both with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2348:43"/>
the Fathers of the primitiue Church, and Lutherans; but they enable themſelues alſo thereby, to affirme (with ſome very litle ſhewe of colour, though it haue no truth at all) that they haue had a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all viſible Church in all the ages ſince Chriſt our Lord; without being ſo eaſily detected to the contrary. And their way is this. When they are preſt by vs to ſhew a continuall viſible Church of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, (which they know well inough that they are not able to produce) thoſe aduerſaryes of ours, who are of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity at all, are wont clearely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that indeede they haue had no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall viſible Church. But ſo alſo they declare, that there is no neceſſity at all that the Church muſt haue beene conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually viſible to the eyes of men. The reſt, who ſee how abſurde this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is, ſay that indeede there muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue bene a viſible Church; but then againe they ſubdiuide themſelues in that opinion. For ſome fewe of them affirme (when they are vrged by vs to ſhewe that viſible Church of theirs) that theirs, and ours, do make but one true Church; and ſo in ſhewing the viſibity of ours, they doe withall (as they ſay)
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2348:44"/>
ſhewe their owne to haue beene viſible. And theſe men treade in this way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they well know, that no other Church but ours can indeed be ſhewed to haue beene viſible through all ages ſince Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>But a third ſort of men there is, who pretend to ſhewe a Church diſtinct from ours, which hath continually been viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in the profeſſion and practiſe of the Proteſtant Religion. Wherein Fox hath ſhewed the way to the gees, who follow him. For in fine, when they are put to name their particular profeſſours of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages; they doe but muſter vp thoſe ſeuerall ſingle falſe doctrines, which haue been held by other heretickes by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle, during tenne or twelue ages ſince Chriſt our Lord; many of which Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines together, themſelues doe now profeſſe in groſſe. For what other men of former times did they euer, or can they euer name, as men of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but ſuch as belieued ſome one or two of thoſe hereticall doctrines, which now themſelues embrace; and wherein they are contrary to vs? But by that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, our aduerſaries might ſay as well, that both they and we, yea and all thoſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2348:44"/>
others alſo, are of one and the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, becauſe we all agree together in many points, though we differ in many more; and though we be excommu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by one an other. And if their belief may be examined, whom our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries cite out of former times, as men to whoſe communion in Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they now lay claime, it will be found, (as hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly beene prooued) that both thoſe former were expreſſe heretickes (euen in the Proteſtants owne opinion as wel as ours) for their miſbeliefe of other things; and that thoſe doctrines, wherein thoſe former heretickes agreed with vs, and diſſented from the Proteſtants, are now moſt vniuſtly condemned by them in our perſons; howſoeuer (for the hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their owne miſery) they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to winke at the ſelfe ſame opinions in them, who were their predeceſſours in hereſie.</p>
               <p>But all this while, it muſt ſtill be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that they make themſelues able to daunce alſo in this Net by the diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they haue framed of <hi>fundamentall</hi> and <hi>not fundamentall.</hi> For if this had not beene deuiſed, but that it might haue beene declared, that the obſtinate beliefe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2348:45"/>
of any one ſingle hereſie depriues a man of ſaluation; and therefore that there is no meanes to make any one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be of the ſame Religion with any other, but by being wholy of the ſame Religion; ſo farre forth at the leaſt, as that he muſt not obſtinately deny any one doctrine thereof, whether it be important more or leſſe, when once, as hath been ſayed, it is lawfully and ſufficiently propounded, and comaunded to be belieued by the true Church: it would inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly haue been made as patent and cleare, as it is true &amp; certaine, that neither when Luther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled from the Church of Chriſt our Lord, nor in any age before his time, there was in the whole world, any one kingdome, or country, or citty, or towne or family of men, or paſtour, or flocke, yea or any one ſingle perſon, ſo much as of Luthers owne, and much leſſe of the now Proteſtant Religion, which is now forſoothe ſo farre refined beyond his.</p>
               <p>To conclude, the making of this diſtinction betweene fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal, &amp; not fundamentall points of faith, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing not to declare which is which, doth ſaue them, with a great part of the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2348:45"/>
ignorant world, from the imputation of Rigour, in their proceeding with vs. For how could they perſecute, as they doe, without extreame note of cruelty? yea or euen how could they diſſent without apparent impiety, from our beliefe and practiſe of thoſe doctrines, wherein we haue had, and ſtill haue preſcription of ſo many ages; if the contrary thereof ſhould be confeſſed by themſelues not to be fundamentall? We muſt not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wonder, if that they ſticke ſo faſt, as they do, to this diſtinction: for hereby it appeers, that they haue wit inough to keep themſelues warme, which they could not do ſo wel without this cloake vpon their backs.</p>
               <p>It is alſo more them probable, that one reaſon, why they are ſo vnwilling to giue in any Catalogue of the <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall points,</hi> is becauſe they know ſoe well how ridiculous they would make themſelues by the infinite variety of their <hi>Catalogues.</hi> For if it be ſo familiar with them to be of different mindes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning particular doctrines, how much more would they be ſo, in this which is a roote of many branches, or rather a monſter of many heads. And ſo there
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2348:46"/>
can be no doubt, but that ſome of them would not be more reſolute in reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fundamentall points into a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row compaſſe, then others would be in enlarging them to a broader. I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what is ſayd by moſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this purpoſe: &amp; becauſe this chapter is growne into length, you ſhall expect that which followes in the next.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>That Protestants neither do, nor dare declare what are their <hi>fundamentall points</hi> of faith; whereby yet they would pretend that they liue in the Communion of the one true Church of Christ our Lord. <hi>CHAPTER IX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is vſuall with many to affirme that the Apoſtles Creede containes all the Fundamentall points of Faith: but theſe men when they are preſſed, grow ſoone aſhamed of that opinion; when they are tould that in the Creede, there is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made at al, either of the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, or of the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, or nature, yea or ſo much as of the name of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Beſides that there are ſo great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences betweene them and vs about the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2348:46"/>
vnderſtanding of the Article of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of Chriſt our Lord into Hell, and that other of the holy Catholike Church; and that alſo, of the communion of Saints, which we belieue and they deny to inuolue both prayers for the dead, &amp; prayers to Saints, as that we ſhould not be much the better, either for our knowing or confeſſing that the Creede containes all the Fundamentall points of Faith, vnles with all there were ſome certaine way, how to vnderſtand them right, and eſpecially vnles vnder the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, which concernes <hi>the holy Catholicke Church,</hi> they would vnderſtand it to be indued with ſo perfect infallibility, and great authority, as that it might teach vs all the reſt. For indeed according to that ſenſe, not only the whole Creede, but euen that ſingle Article of the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church might be ſaid to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the reaſon of all our Faith ſo Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentally, as that we ſhould neede noe other guide then that.</p>
               <p>But if we vnderſtand it otherwiſe, the Scripture it ſelfe ſpeakes of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar errours, which are da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable in them, by whome they are embraced; and yet they are not at all againſt any expreſſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2348:47"/>
doctrine of the Creede. As namely where <hi>S. Paule</hi> calls it a doctrine of diuells, to forbid marriage, and meats: which, by the way, is not to be vnderſtood of the chaſtity, and faſts of the Catholicke Church (as Proteſtants do moſt peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely affirme) which knowes that thoſe things are lawfull, but that yet it is moſt gratefull to God, when his ſeruants, for his loue, depriue themſelues of thoſe delights; but of the hereſie of the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hees, as <hi>S. Austen</hi> doth expreſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, who forbad both marriage and meats, as being abominable and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure through the inſtitution thereof, which they ſaid was deriued from a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſecond ill co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicioned God, of their owne making. In like manner <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaith, that <hi>S. Paule</hi> in his Epiſtles had written certaine thinges, which were hard to be vnderſtood, and which the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and vnſtable did peruert to their owne deſtruction. <hi>S. Auſten</hi> declares vpon this place, that the places miſunderſtood concerned the doctrine of Iuſtification, which ſome miſconceaued to be by faith alone, by occaſion of what <hi>S. Paule</hi> had written to the Romanes. And of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to countermine that errour, he ſaith
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2348:47"/>
that <hi>S. Iames</hi> wrote his Epiſtle, and prooued therein that good works were abſolutely neceſſary to the acte of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Here vpon we may obſerue two things; the one that an errour in this point alone, is by the iudgment of <hi>S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to worke their deſtruction, who em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it: and the other, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creede which ſpeakes no one word thereof, is no good rule to let vs knowe all the fundamentall point of faith.</p>
               <p>Others ſay, that the booke of the 39. Articles declares all the fundamentall points of Faith, according to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of England; but that alſo is moſt abſurdly affirmed. For as it is true, that they declare in ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed manner (which yet indeed is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely confuſed) what the Church of England in moſt things belieues; ſo is it as true, that they are very carefull, that they be not too clearely vnderſtood. And therefore in many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſies, whereof that booke ſpeakes, it comes not at all to the maine difficulty of the queſtion betweene them and vs; and eſpecially in thoſe of the Church, and Free will. For whereas there are two maine Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies concerning the Church; namely
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:2348:48"/>
whether the Catholicke Church of our Lord muſt not euer be viſible to the eyes of men, though at ſome times more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly then at others; and whether the ſaid Church be infallible in the definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Faith (in both which points we hold the affirmatiue and they the negatiue;) they dare not declare in this publique manner what they hold therein. And ſo alſo in that of Free Wil,<note place="margin">Art. 10.</note> they only affirme thereof <hi>in haec verba.</hi> The condition of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> is ſuch, that he cannot turne, &amp; prepare himſelfe by his owne naturall ſtrength, &amp; good workes, to faith, &amp; calling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God; wherfore we haue no power to do good workes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and acceptable to God, without the grace of God preuenting vs, that we may haue a good will, and working with vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue that goodwil. Now this is true Catholick Doctrine, which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue better them they. But they declare not the while, whether or no a man haue freedome of will to do a good worke or not to do it, when firſt he is inſpired, and moued to it by God Almighties grace; which we affirme, &amp; they deny, &amp; which is the only knott of our queſtion, &amp; the point vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſo many other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Doctrines depend.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:2348:48"/>Soe alſo do they play at faſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooſe, when in the ſixt Article, of holy Scripture, they enumerate al thoſe books of the <hi>old Testament,</hi> which they allow to be Canonicall; wherein by the way, they are rather <hi>Iewes</hi> then <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> for not admitting the bookes of <hi>Iudith</hi> the <hi>Machabees,</hi> &amp; diuers others into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. And they trifle, alſo when they tell vs, that they vnderſtand thoſe only bookes both of the <hi>old</hi> and <hi>newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to be Canonicall, <hi>of whoſe authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty there was neuer any doubt in the Church.</hi> For they know as well as we, that the <hi>Apocalips,</hi> the Epiſtle of <hi>S. Iames, S. Iude,</hi> and one of <hi>S. Peters,</hi> were not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged till prooffes were made, during the ſpace of three or fower hundred yeares after Chriſt our Lord. And yet theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue beene pleaſed out of their great grace, to admit them, though the <hi>Machabees</hi> muſt be reiected, becauſe they ſpeake of prayer for the dead. But ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in the meane time, what this booke of Articles ſayeth concerning the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall bookes of the <hi>new Teſtament.</hi> It ſaith only this. <hi>All the bookes of new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, as they are commonly receaued, we doe receaue, and account them for Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:2348:49"/>
But why doe they not particularly enumerate all the bookes which they acknowledge to be of the <hi>new Teſtament,</hi> as they had done them of the <hi>old?</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe they muſt ſo haue named thoſe bookes of <hi>S. Iames</hi> and others for Canonicall, which the <hi>Lutherans</hi> haue caſt out of their Canon. A mad peece of vnity, God wot, when theſe refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of the Church, according forſooth to Scripture (if you will take their word) cannot ſo much as agree about the very Canon it ſelfe of the Scripture.</p>
               <p>But abſtracting from all theſe inſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, wherewith that booke of Articles is full fraught, they doe not ſo much as ſay, that the Articles of Doctrine, which they deliuer are fundamentall, either all, or halfe, or any one thereof; or that they are neceſſarily to be belieued by them, or the contrary damnable if it be belieued by vs; but they are glad to walke in a cloude, for the reaſons which haue beene already toucht.</p>
               <p>Maiſter <hi>Rogers</hi> indeede, in the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis which he makes of thoſe nyne and thirty Articles, ſpeakes lowd inough by way of taxing the doctrine of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> as being contrary to that of the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2348:49"/>
Church of England; and he giues it as many ill names, as his impure ſpirit can deuiſe; &amp; affirmes amongſt other things, that many Papiſts, and namely the Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcans bluſh not to affirme that <hi>S. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> is the holy Ghoſt:<note place="margin">Fol. 23.</note> And that Chriſt is the Sauiour of men, but one Mother <hi>Iane</hi> is the Sauiour of woemen, a moſt execrable of <hi>Postellus</hi> the Ieſuit;<note place="margin">Fol. 14.</note> with a great deale of ſuch baſe traſh as this. And yet his booke is declared <hi>to haue beene pervſed, and by the lawfull authority of the Church of England permitted to be publicke.</hi> But yet, euen Maiſter <hi>Rogers</hi> himſelfe, is not ſo valiant as to tell vs in particular which point of their Doctrine is funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall to ſaluation, and which is not.</p>
               <p>Much leſſe is there any apparance that euer the Church of England ſhould doe it; ſince euen now we haue ſeene, that it dares not, in diuerſe points, ſoe much as declare in publicke manner, that it profeſſes the expreſſe contrary of what we held. Nay we are not likely to ſee the <hi>fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>damental</hi> points of Faith, whereof they talke ſo lowd, to be auowed by ſo much as either of the Vniuerſities, yea or yet by any one Colledge, or ſociety of learned men amongſt them. And the reaſon of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2348:50"/>
their reſeruation in this kind is playne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For if, when they write ioyntly, and in a body, they ſhould be conuinced of any abſurdity or errour, by the teſtimony either of the ancient Fathers on the one ſide, or the Lutherans on the other, their maine cauſe would receaue a mortall wounde; becauſe ſo their Church, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Vniuerſities or Colledges would plainly appeare to be controlled, and confuted, eitheir by the Fathers, or their fellow ghoſpellers: whereas now when they ſpeake or write, but in the name or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of particular men, one of them will not thinke, that himſelfe, or his cauſe is much preiudiced, if any other of them be found guylty of errour; and in ſuch caſes, it is vſuall for them to ſay, what care I if Doctour <hi>Morton</hi> ſay this, or Doctour <hi>White</hi> ſay that? and the like. For this reaſon it is, that I haue heard ſome Catholickes affirme, (and that, to my thinking, with great reaſon) that they would hold it to be no ill worke for them, if the pretended Colledge of Chelſy, or any other, were founded by Proteſtants expreſly for writing bookes of controuerſie, by common conſent. But I belieue I ſhall not ſee them halt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2348:50"/>
vpon that leg, for feare leaſt they ſhould be found to be lame of both.</p>
               <p>On the otherſide, at times, they make eager inuectiues againſt vs, for declaring ſo many, yea and all the Doctrines of our Church to be <hi>Fundamentall;</hi> ſo far forth as that whoſoeuer refuſes obſtinatly to belieue any one of them, doth forfette the ſaluation of his ſoule. And in the ſtrength of this zeale of theirs, Doctour <hi>Dunne</hi> in a ſermon made before his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty at his firſt happy coming to this Crowne, doth bitterly exclame againſt the Catholicke Romane Church as mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euery toy to be <hi>Fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>damentall.</hi> Where, by the way, he takes his pleaſure vpon vs, &amp; ſayes that we Papiſts will not let Proteſtants be ſaued, though they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the ſame Creede, and the ſame faith with vs; vnles withall they will belieue, the ſame Mathematicks, and gouerne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by the ſame Kale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, which to omit other poorneſſes of his, was ſoe weake and meane a ieſt, ſo miſbecom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Audience and of the place he helde, as being fitter indeed for ſome Ordinary, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a Chappel or Church; and withall ſo very vntrue, if he were in earneſt, that vnles the pride of his owne
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2348:51"/>
conceit had raiſed vp a duſt to put out his eyes, he could not but haue ſeene the ſenſeleſnes of what he ſaid, euen whileſt he was ſpeaking: ſince we the Romane Catholickes in this kingdome do rather gouerne our ſelues at this day, by the leſſe perfect Kalender, which now is vſed in this place, then by the other, which is both the better (euen by the iudgment of learned Proteſtants) &amp; is authorized by the Catholicke Church abroade. Letting he world ſee thereby, how willingly we can accommodate to them in all things, which belong not meerely to Religion. But Maiſter Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour forgot himſelfe worſe ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. For hauing grauely admoniſhed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before, not to account things arbitrary to be neceſſary, nor to call ſuperſtructions foundations, nor to eſteeme that euery little thing in Religion ſhould be able to depriue a man of ſaluation, he takes the paynes to wipe out with a wet finger the whole ſubſtance, and drifte of all his owne diſcourſe, by ſaying to his effect: That differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in beliefe, in points, which are not very important, is not to preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice a mans ſaluation, vnles by not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them he commit a diſobedience
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2348:51"/>
with all, for (ſaith he) <hi>Obedience indeede is of the Eſsence of Religion.</hi> Which vpon the whole matter, is the very thing we ſay; and the very thing whereby he croſſes the whole ſcope of his owne ſermon. For if a mans diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and direction of the Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning an inferiour point of Doctrine, do impugne <hi>the very eſſenſe of Religion,</hi> it will follow that their diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of points <hi>Fundamentall</hi> or <hi>not Fundamentall</hi> (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they would inferre that a man can not looſe his ſaluation but for miſbelief in ſome few mayne points of Religion, and not in the reſt) is abſurd and vaine, and detractiue both of Doctour <hi>Dunnes</hi> Doctrine laſt mentioned, and of their owne obiection of vncharitablenes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, for ſaying that men dying in different Religions cannot be ſaued. And withall that this diſtinction will not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them from committing the crime of ſeparation from the Church of Chriſt our Lord, and in ſwaruing from the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections thereof; in which caſe, all the Doctrines of the Church are found to be <hi>Fundamentall</hi> towards ſaluation.</p>
               <p>And this ſhall ſerue for a diſchardge, both of what they obiect againſt our vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2348:52"/>
in faith, and of what they alleadge in the behalfe of theirs. And in the meane time, I conceaue that I haue alſo ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſecured and ſettled thoſe two mayne groundes vpon which this whole, diſcourſe is turned. Namely firſt that there is but one true faith, and one true Religion and Church, out of which there is no ſaluation: and ſecondly that both Catholickes and Proteſtants can not poſſible be accounted to be of that one Religion, Church &amp; Faith. And now for the finall proofe of this laſt point according euen to their practiſe as well as ours; let my Reader but looke vpon the body of their lawes made againſt vs, and eſpecially vpon the Preambles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, wherein they plentifully ſhew how hatefull an opinion they haue of our Church; Let him looke vpon the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Acts of State, which haue iſſued from my Lords of the Counſell; Let him looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which haue beene made and publiſhed from time to time; Let him looke vpon the large co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, which haue beene granted to Purſiuants, whereby that ſcume of the world, hath been and is enabled, both to ranſome &amp; ranſacke vs at their pleaſure;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2348:52"/>
Let him looke vpon thoſe ſpeeches, which haue been vttered in both houſes of Parliament, not only againſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours, but euen the profeſſion it ſelfe of our Religion; and how his moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſty, hath been importuned by their Petitions, to add more weight to our miſeries: for thus it will eaſily be ſeene, how falſe how rotten, how ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, how Idolatrous, how dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, how damnable, and euen deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue of all truth and goodnes they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelues to eſteeme our Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in fine that we carry ſuch a marke of the Beaſt in our foreheads as muſt needs, in their opinion, ſhut vp the gates of Heauen againſt vs, and ſet open the iawes of Hell to deuoure and ſwallowe vs vp. So that certainely we are no more of one Church with them in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, then they are of one with vs in ours. And now there will remaine noe more but a ſhort Recapitulation of what hath been deliuered more at large, for the finiſhing of this diſcourſe, to which I will now betake my ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:2348:53"/>
               <head>A recapitulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole diſcourſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it followes vpon the confeſsion of both parties, that the Catholickes, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, are not both of them ſaueable in their ſeuerall Religions, without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereof before they dy; and that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes must therefore be no longer held vncharitable for ſaying ſo: but thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants are shewed to be Libertines, who ſay the contrary. <hi>CHAPTER X.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce the Faith, Religion, &amp; Church, hath beene prooued both by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures and Fathers, as alſo by vnanſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reaſons, which haue beene drawne both from the very groundes of true Faith, and from the nature and ſpirit of Hereſy and Schiſme, and finally by the Confeſſion of both parties, to be but only one; and that out of that one, there is noe ſaluation to be obtayned: Since the difference concerning the Doctrine of faith betweene Catholickes &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, are ſo many, ſo important, and ſo reſolutely maintained, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning both the Canon of Scriptures, the number &amp;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2348:53"/>
nature of Sacraments, the authority of traditions, the ſupreme Iudge of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, the viſible heade of the Church, the iuſtification of ouer ſoules, the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lewe of our good workes, the liberty of our will, the poſſibility of keeping the Commandements, the relations which runne betweene the men of this life on the one ſide, and both the ſoules in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and the Saints in Heauen on the other: Since, beſides our differences in points of Doctrine, we ſwarue alſo from one an other in points of diſcipline, and haue ſeparated our ſelues &amp; haue mutual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated one another: Since we hold them to liue in hereſie and ſchiſme, and they vs in affected ignorance, groſſe ſuperſtition and Idolatry, and are dayly making Sermons and bookes and edicts and lawes againſt one another: it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that either both they, and we muſt not be ſaued, if we dy vnrepe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tant of our ſeuerall Religions; or elſe that the whole world hath beene in a dreame of three thouſand yeares old, euer ſince <hi>Moyſes</hi> time, which furniſhed vs, with the firſt proofe that there muſt be vnity in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and obedience in the profeſſours thereof, &amp; that ſuch as ſhould obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2348:54"/>
trangreſſe, were ordained to be put to a firſt death, which might ſerue them for a Preface to their ſecond deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Which truth being once graunted, I truſt they will not take it ill, at our hands, if we hope well of our ſelues in our owne way; and conſequently if we conceaue that we haue no cauſe to hope well of them, if they dy impeditent in theirs, they haue no reaſon to be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with vs: and the leſſe ſince the Lutherans declare ſo expreſly and reſolutely that the Reſolution of the Sacramentaries, that is to ſay, of our Engliſh Proteſtants, is alſo damnable, as hath been ſeene. And this not only for the hereſie which they hold in point of the Sacrament, but for many others alſo, as appeares by thoſe authours of theirs, whom I cited before. So that ſtill I ſee leſſe and leſſe colour, why they ſhould except againſt vs, as if we wanted charity, for ſaying that of them, which when they liſt, they not only take liberty to ſay of vs, but euen of one another alſo; and yet do not thinke that they offend Charitie therein.</p>
               <p>As for vs, we neither do, nor can with any reaſon conceaue, that they breake the lawe of charity towards vs
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2348:54"/>
(ſuppoſing their owne Religion to be true) in that they allow not ſaluation to vs, if we dye in ours; which conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently muſt be falſe. And if ours be a falſe Religion, (as it muſt needes be, if their Church be true, and that we obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately refuſe to obay it) we cannot be ſaued by the profeſſion thereof. And ſo therefore, on the other ſide, if ours be true (as euen they muſt giue vs leaue to thinke it, and as infallibly we belieue it to be) theirs muſt then be no leſſe falſe, then ours is true. Now ſuppoſing this on both ſides, it will not be want of Charity in either of vs, both to hold, and declare, the others Religion to be inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible with ſaluation: nay it will be want of Charity if we do it not.</p>
               <p>For men are not ſo made for them ſelues, as that they muſt not alſo procure to do their neighbours good, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in that, which moſt imports. And beſides the generall tye of one part of mankind to another (whereof we are put in minde ſo many wayes) the holy Scripture it ſelfe is often pointing vs out to our duty in this kind; and moſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially it doth in one paſſage of <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus</hi> lay a direct obligation vpon vs, in
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2348:55"/>
theſe moſt binding words;<note place="margin">Cap. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Mandauit vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuique Deus de proximo ſuo. God hath laied a charge vpon euery man, that he looke to his neighbour.</hi> Which as it warrants not the buſie or medling humour of any priuate man, to intrude himſelfe into the ſecret affaires of another, nor obliges him ſo much as euen to the reprooffe of his knowne ſinnes, (when he hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther charge ouer that perſon, nor hath hope of amendement by it, and when it is not agreable otherwiſe to the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces and rules of charity, which ought to be conducted and carryed on by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian prudence;) ſo yet on the otherſide, it layes not only a Counſelle, but a ſtrict commandement, not only vpon ſome one, but vpon euery one; not to omit opportunity, whereby a man may pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently be in hope, either to doe his neighbour any important good, or elſe to diuert him from any thing, which may doe him any conſiderable hurt.</p>
               <p>Now if a priuate man muſt not only be excuſed, if according to the rules of Chriſtian piety and prudence, he aſſiſt his neighbour in doing well, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the danger wherein he is, if he doe otherwiſe, but he ſhall not be excuſable
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2348:55"/>
in the ſight of God, if he diſchardge not this duty; how much more highly ſhall the Church of Chriſt our Lord be both authorized, and obliged to inſtruct Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the right way, and to reduce ſuch others as are in the wrong, by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them vnderſtand their danger of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting damnation?</p>
               <p>Nay we ſee by that which paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Almighty God and the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> that he was appointed to ſtand Centinell ouer the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to heare Gods word out of his owne mouth, and ſo to announce it to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in his name; and that God ſaid thus to him, <hi>Si dicente me ad impium &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezechiel cap. 3.</note> If when I ſhall ſay to the wicked ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou ſhalt dye the death, thou declare it not to him, nor aduiſe him to returne from his wicked way, that he may liue; that wicked man ſhall dy in his iniquity, but I will require his blood at thy handes. But if thou anounce it to him, and that yet he will not returne from his ſinne and from his wicked way, that man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhall dye in his owne ſinne, but as for thee, thou ſhalt haue freed thy ſoule from death.</p>
               <p>Now therefore if a ſingle Prophet,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2348:56"/>
being called to that office by Almighty God, be obliged, vnder the paine of his owne damnation, to aduiſe men to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from their wickednes; how much more preciſely will this obligation lye vpon the Church of God, which hath the chardge ouer all Chriſtian ſoules, to teach them that Doctrine which is true, and to let them ſee the danger wherein they are of hell fire, if they continue to profeſſe that which is falſe? For the word of God, whether it be written in holy Scripture, or vnwritten and ſo deliuered from hand to hand by Tradition, is his reuealed will; and the Church is his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſadour Leidger in this world, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and announce that word and will of his to mankind; and to bring them into league with God, as <hi>S. Paule</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of him ſelfe, and of the other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours and Doctours of the Church;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5</note> 
                  <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatione pro Chriſto fungimur &amp;c. We are Embaſſadours on the part of Chriſt,</hi> with inſtructions for the reconciling of man to God. And accordingly <hi>S. Paule</hi> was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to let men ſee their caſe, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the danger wherein ſinners were. For we haue ſeene how he warned men to take heede of the ſpeech of hereticks
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2348:56"/>
as of a Cancer; and elſe where, to auoid them if they did not firſt reforme them ſelues, after they had beene reprooued once or twice; as alſo that ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the vnity of faith were peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who attended to the ſpirit of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and to the Doctrine of diuells; and a great deale more of that kind, which you ſhall find related before in the ninth chapter: which clearly and fully ſhewes what opinion the holy Scripture hath of heretickes.</p>
               <p>Beſides all this if a man ſhall eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally be damned for committing of one theft, or one act of ſimple fornication, vnles he repent himſelfe thereof before he dy,<note place="margin">Gal. 5. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulta. decapeſ. relig.</note> which is cleare by <hi>S. Paules</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe text: much more, as Father <hi>Leſſius</hi> ſhewes, ſhall he incurre thoſe eternall torments for hereſie, which is a moſt grieuous kind of infidelity, and which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes in it ſelfe ſo many other moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſinnes, as namely blaſphemies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Sacraments, ſcoffes and ſcornes, a prophanation of holy things, a hatred and perſecution of true Religion, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Church and her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates; ſacriledge, pride, obſtinacy, ſchiſme and rebellion againſt the ſupreme Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:2348:57"/>
Magiſtrats. How great torment therefore, I ſay, ſhall any man eternally endure, for the ſinne of Hereſie, which is more grieuous then thouſands of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications and thefts?</p>
               <p>It will not therefore ſerue a mans turne towards eternall life, if being out of the Communion of Gods Church, he carry himſelfe otherwiſe as ſweetly, as ciuilly as can be deuiſed; and that men praiſe him for a worthy perſon, an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, the beſt neighbour in a whole kingdome, one who owes no man a penny, one who is curteous to all the world, who neuer ſweares an oath, nor giues offence to any, in any kind. Theſe are all goods things, but theſe are not all thoſe good things, which are required of him who will be ſaued. For whileſt ſuch an one is ſo kind and ciuill to man, he is both vnkind &amp; cruell towards Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, if he be rebellious to that Church which was purchaſſed by the death of his only ſonne. But it ſeemes we are ſtill made of that mould, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>S. Hierom</hi> ſpeaks after this manner, <hi>Nos in Dei iniurijs benigni ſumus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In c. 16. Matt.</note> 
                  <hi>in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s contumelijs odia exercemus. We are eaſy &amp; remiſse towards ſuch as ar iniuriours
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2348:57"/>
to God; but we are reuinge full, when there is question of righting thoſe wronges which are done to our ſelues.</hi> But withall, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leages the example of <hi>Hely</hi> in the booke of kings, againſt this ill cuſtome, ſaying, <hi>Si peccauerit vir in virum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Reg. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>placari ei potest Deus: ſi autem in Deum quis peccauerit, quis orabit pro eo? If one man offend an other, God may yet be appeaſed towards him: but if any man ſin againſt God, who shall pray for that man?</hi> A very different dictamen from that which raignes now in the world; where a man, who giues men no offence, ſhall be celebrated by men for a kind of Saint, though withall his whole life be conſumed in ſinning againſt God, by infidelity, by ſecret blaſphemy, by hereſie, and by all that pride and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which it involues againſt God and his Church, together with contempt &amp; ſcorne, as hath been ſayd, of all thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Ceremonies, and almoſt all thoſe holy Sacraments, which his diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty hath ordained for our eternal good, with ſo much coſt to him ſelfe.</p>
               <p>But Saints and men of God, who ſee with clearer eyes then others, make a contrary iudgment of theſe things: and ſo alſo are they very remiſſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2348:58"/>
is done but to themſelues; but rigorous, when peruerſe men will needs be put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting affronts vpon Almighty God. The Eccleſiaſticall ſtory is full of examples in this kind. See but how <hi>S. Iohn</hi> carryed himſelfe towards <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Polycarpe</hi> to <hi>Marcion,</hi> and <hi>S. Antony</hi> to the <hi>Arrians;</hi> and a thouſand others. And leaſt it ſhould be thought that Saints fall not foule, but only vpon ſuch Hereticks as deny the very prime Articles of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which concerne either God the Father, or the immediat perſon of Chriſt our Lord himſelfe: caſt but an eye vpon <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> that milde &amp; mercifull man of God, &amp; ſee how he treates the hereticks of his time, who had too much affinity with thoſe of ours, as you will perceaue by his cenſure of them; but yet it was for certaine points which ſeemed not to trench ſo deepe into the Chriſtian Faith. But howſoeuer, he ſpeakes of them in no gentler a ſtill then this,<note place="margin">Serm. in Cantic. 66.</note> 
                  <hi>Videte detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctores, videte canes; irrident nos, quia bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizamus infantes; quòd oramus pro mortuis; quòd Sanctorum ſuffragia poſtulamus. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold theſe detractours, beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld theſe dogs. they ſcoffe as vs, becauſe we baptiſe infants; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we pray for the dead; and becauſe we
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2348:58"/>
beg the prayers of the Saincts.</hi> So that ſtill we ſee into this truth, more and more. That how ſmooth ſoeuer the face, and how ſweete ſoeuer the words, and how ciuill ſoeuer the cariage be; yet if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie be in the heart, it is of all others the moſt odious and offenſiue thing, both to Almighty God, and to all good men, who haue his honour in high account. Yea and euen how kind, and ciuill ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they ſeeme to their neighbours and friends in morall things, ſuch eſpecially as they ſee often, and ſalute, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with; yet you may obſerue by that ſaying of <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> that they are cruell inough to ſuch as they ſee not. And with all their ciuillity and curteſy and ſuauity in ordinary conuerſation, they can find in their hereticall hearts, at a clap to rob all dead men, of the helpe &amp; comfort of the prayers of the liuing; &amp; al liuing me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of the prayers of the Saints who are in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the ſame Saintes, of all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which Catholickes pay to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here on earth; to omit in this place, their infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite &amp; innumerable detractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, &amp; reproaches of the whole Church of God. Al which I haue not ſayd, either by way of aggrauating their ſins, or of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienating
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:2348:59"/>
men from their perſons; which I eſteeme, and loue, and deſire to ſerue with my whole heart; but only, to the end that they may know their owne caſe, and conſider well, what kind of thing hereſie is, and how hatefull in it ſelfe to God, and man; that ſo, by the diuine goodnes, they may grow to change, both their names and natures; &amp; paſſe from being enemies, to become children of that one true Church, out of which ther is no ſaluation.</p>
               <p>In the meane time it is more them clear, that the chardge, which Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants lay vpon vs, as wanting Charity, for ſaying that their Religion vnrepented deſtroyes ſaluation; muſt needs be now transferred from vs, and imputed with as much reaſon to him, who hath layed (as hath been ſeene) an obligation euen vpon all Chriſtians, and much more vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church, and the Paſtours thereof, to declare the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers which they incurre, who are departed from the Communion of the holy Catholicke Church. And as truly, yea &amp; much more probablely, may they affirme, that the holy Fathers of the Primitiue Church wanted Charity, for the ſtrictnes, which they vſed in conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:2348:59"/>
men to Hell, as heretickes, for their obſtinancy in holding ſome one ſingle Doctrine of it ſelfe, which yet was not ſomtimes ſo very importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> That <hi>S. Paule</hi> wanted charity, when he excluded men from heauen for thoſe ſins of frailty, to which we are daily ſollicited, euen by the very nature and condicion of our owne fleſh and blood; and in particular alſo for <hi>diſſentions</hi> and <hi>ſects,</hi> which ſignify <hi>hereſy</hi> in that place. That the holy Ghoſt wanted charity, being the hand which guided the Apoſtles finger, to write ſo ſeuerely as he did. That Chriſt our Lord wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted Charity, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunding that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be held <hi>for no better then Pagans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>and Publicans, if in any thing of ſcandall, and much more of doctrine concerning faith they diſobeyed the Church:</hi> for his precept of obedience was indefinite, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our obedience muſt not be limited, only to this, or that. That God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther himſelfe wanted Charity, who ſent <hi>Chore, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiron</hi> aliue,<note place="margin">Numb. 16.</note> and headlong into hell, for a meer act of ſchiſme, and commanded that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer would not obey the ſentence of the Prieſt for the time being, ſhould, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other remedy, be put to death.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:2348:60"/>
And laſtly that <hi>Luther</hi> himſelfe, and his moſt learned Diſciples wanted Charity, not only for defaming the Church of Rome, as the ſeate of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> the whore of Babylon, and the Beaſt of the Apocalips, which printes the marke of damnation vpon the foreheads of her Children; but for condemning alſo all Caluiniſts, for their hereſie, concerning the bleſſed Sacrament, beſides many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which are both imputed and proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vpon them, by the Lutherans.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Luther</hi> and his Diſciples, it coſts me little to lay them a ſide, as not importing much what they ſay, ſaue that their authority is <hi>argumentum ad homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> againſt al ſuch Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Libertins, of this nation, as ſo vniuſtly chardge vs with want of Charity towards them, for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that if they dye in Proteſtancy, they cannot be ſaued. But that which I haue ſhewed <hi>à parte rei;</hi> namely that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Primitiue Church, that the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>S. Paule,</hi> nay that God the Father, the Sonne, &amp; the holy Ghoſt haue both practiſed, and impoſed vpon all Chriſtians, and eſpecially vpon the Church and Church-men to declare the danger wherein ſinners are to looſe their
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2348:60"/>
ſoules, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing in ſinne; muſt needes ſuffice to exempt vs in the iudgment of any indifferent morall man, from offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt Charity for doing the like.</p>
               <p>It is not therefore want of Charity in vs, to affirme the danger of their ſtate, who are in errour, out of a moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian deſire to ſee them deliuered from the ſame: but it is too euident, that their miſlike of vs, vpon this occaſion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes in them out of Libertiniſme and their too great good fellowſhip in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the ſoule, and out of the meane conceit, which they haue framed in their mindes, of the vnity of Faith, and of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion both in Doctrine and diſcipline with the Catholicke Church, and of the entirenes of the infallible truth, and the vnſpotted ſeruice of Almighty God.</p>
               <p>And what indeed doe they, but ſhew by their whole courſe, that they deſire and reſolue, to belieue, and profeſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the occaſion; and to comply with the ſuperiour powers of this world; and to obay the motions of appetite and ſenſe, without being euer ſo much as tould, if they can chooſe, that they muſt looſe heauen for their labour? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may be ſeene, that the children, are
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2348:61"/>
in this, as like their Mother as they can looke. For who perceaues not, that the Proteſtant Church, doth rather carry a reſpect to outward Conformity, then to reall vnity in matter of Religion; &amp; that indeed, they are but as in ieſt, when there is ſpeech of ſauing ſoules in any one Church, rather then in another.</p>
               <p>It is true that they make both lawes and Canons, whereby they oblidge me, vnder a world of penalties, to frequent their Churches, and to receaue their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; but without caring greately, whether men belieue their Doctrine to be true or no. For I put this caſe. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who were knowne to be wholly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in his heart to the Catholicke Faith, ſhould yet, for the ſauing of his lands or goods, reſolue to comply with their lawes by going to their Churches, and by receauing their Communion; yea and withall ſhould declare in company the day before, that he was reſolued to do ſo the day after, for the only ſauing of his eſtate, and for the ſhewing of his obedience to the Kings lawes; though yet withall, he were perſuaded that their Sacraments were vnlawfull, and their Church impure: would that Miniſter,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:2348:61"/>
refuſe to let him goe to his Seruice, and or to communicate with the reſt? Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly he would not; and we ſee dayly that they doe not in like occaſions. For that Church, as I ſayd, aſpires not to Vnity, but Vniformity.</p>
               <p>But the proceeding of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church is very different, and hath that diuine truth, which was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our Lord to her care, in ſo high account, that if ſhe haue but iuſt cauſe to ſuſpect, that any man belieues not in his hart, as ſhe teaches; ſhe is ſo farre from obliging him vnder pecuniary mulcts, to repaier to her ſeruice and Sacraments, that ſhe will by no meanes, admit him thereunto, till he haue firſt cleare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of that ſuſpicion, and ſufficienly ſhewed himſelfe free, from any ſuch want of beliefe. Thus doth the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church of this age proceed, and thus alſo did the ſame Church proceede in the moſt Primitiue times: In ſo much as that then there were, and now there ar, certaine me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deputed, belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches, who were called <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarij.</hi> Whoſe duty was and is, to attend within at the Church doores, of purpoſe to hinder their being preſent at the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:2348:62"/>
of diuine Myſteries, whom they may know to be obſtinately auerſt, either from belieuing any part of the Doctrine, or from liuing vnder the diſcipline, of the Catholicke Church.</p>
               <p>This Church, which is enriched and endowed with the holy Ghoſt, and conſequently with ſpirituall Fortitude, which is one of the ſeauen prime gifts thereof, proceeds like a body, which knowes it ſelfe to belong to an omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent head; and feares not to avowe, both what it ſaith, and what it doth. And as, on the one ſide, ſhe expreſſes all the ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity which can be conceaued, and is moſt ready to wrap vp the moſt enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſinners of the world, and the moſt mortall enemyes which ſhe hath, in the very bowells of her compaſſion, if they will come to God in the way of pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; ſo yet withall, on the other ſide, if men will preſume to be ſoe vaſtly proud, as to preferre their owne fancies before her wiſedome, which was ſent downe from Heauen for, the direction of the world; and if, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding her moſt charitable endeauours to reduce them, they will yet add contempt and obſtinacy to their other ſinnes, ſhe threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2348:62"/>
them with the danger wherein they are; and ſhe goes on ſo farre, if ſhe finde cauſe, as to ſeparate them, in the quality of heretickes, from her Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and proceeds not againſt them as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Traitours to Princes, or ſtates, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that poore ſhifte of Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (whoſe guylty Conſciences make them not dare, though their hearts be well bent that way) to puniſh our Prieſts ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitally, as for a corrupt Religion; but they ſet vpon them impudent and falſe pretext of Treaſon. For as the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church is moſt perfectly charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo withall ſhe thinkes ſhe cannot expreſſe that vertue better, then by clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely diſtinguiſhing betweene truth and falſe hood, and by exhorting men to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the one, and to auoid the other; ſo farre off is ſhe from demeriting, by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Proteſtants knowe that if they dye impenitent in that Religion, they looſe their ſoules.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>THE CONCLVSION.</head>
               <p>IN the meane time it is a moſt wofull caſe, chat whileſt they will be blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs for the want of Charity in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:2348:63"/>
them, there ſhould be ſo few of them, who haue ſo much compaſſion and Charity towards themſelues, as to flye from their extreame danger of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death. And that ſuch a world of worthy people being drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp by pride in the vnderſtanding part of the minde, and dragged downe by the diſorderly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the will, ſhould be ſoe very glad to caſt themſelues away, and that for euer.</p>
               <p>Our Lord giue all men grace, to feele in their very hearts, what a huge miſery it is, to be in ſtate of any mortall ſinne, but eſpecially of this preſent Hereſy, which both is grieuous in it ſelfe, and is beſides, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual nourſery of other ſins, by meanes of thoſe corrupt principles, euen concerning life, which vnder the falſe colours of purity, &amp; piety, &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty, &amp; the light of the ghoſpell, it is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to infuſe into the heart of man.</p>
               <p>For when they teach men, that there is no merit belonging to good worke, (though they be confeſt by vs to flowe, but from the grace &amp; goodnes of Chriſt our Lord) what courage do they giue men to be frequent, and cheerefull in doing of good workes? And what cauſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:2348:63"/>
can they aſſigne, why men ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne from ſinne, when they teach them that the beſt workes which are perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the greateſt Saints in the world, are no better then ſinnes, and they in their owne nature mortall? Nay when they teach men that the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God are not poſſibly to be kept by any man, (euen with the helpe of that diuine grace, which hath been pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed and merited for vs, by Chriſt our Lord, and is communicated to the ſoules of his ſeruants by faith and loue) what reaſon can they haue, either to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort men to keepe Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or to reprooue them for infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the ſame? Yea &amp; yet further, when they profeſſe that men haue not ſo much as Free will to do any one good worke at all, euen when they are firſt moued, and aſſiſted towards it by the good grace of God, (for without that grace, all Catholicks profeſſe that no man is able ſo much as to thinke one good thought in order to ſaluation) with what ſence can they encourage men to doe any thing which is good, or with what iuſtice can they puniſh them for omitting the ſame: ſince it hath no dependa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at all, in
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:2348:64"/>
the leaſt degree vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their own Free wil?</p>
               <p>If therefore now at laſt, they would giue me leaue, I would beſeech them to looke with ſteadfaſt eyes, vpon the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſtate wherein they are; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, that our Lord is ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good in himſelfe, and hath bene ſoe gracious to vs, that he deſerue to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored, and ſerued, though all the world ſay nay. And they are happy miſeries which are indured in honour of ſuch a Maieſty as his; whoſe infinite power, &amp; wiſedome, are as if they were but meere inſtruments of his infinite goodnes, for the conueighing of graces downe to vs, and the drawing of vs thereby vp to him.</p>
               <p>The ſinnes of this world, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of Hereſie and Schiſme, which are the very rootes and ſources of millions of ſinnes, giue matter of ſad meditation to the minde of thoſe men, who behold theſe things with a cleare ſight, yea and euen although (by way of ſuppoſition) there were no voluntary and malitious ſinnes committed in the world, yet were it miſery inough for a man to liue out of the communion of the holy Catholicke Church with loſſe of time, in doing good, wherein ſuch ineſtimable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2348:64"/>
might be acquired. For ſuppoſing that a man be a true member of that Church, (for as much as concernes his beliefe;) and that (for as much concernes his life) he be in ſtate of grace, there is no mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of time, wherein by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God (which is euer both preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and cooperating with the will of man) the ſame man may not procure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace, either by the doing of ſome one good deede, or by the ſaying of ſome one good word, or by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of ſome one good thought, to the honour and glory of our Lord God. Nor is there any weakneſſe of body, or want of learning, or of other habilityes of the minde, or any diſtreſſe in fortune, which can clipp the wings (that is to ſay the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affections) of the ſoule, from ſoaring, and ſtruggling thus towards heauen. Now for euery degree of new grace, there is, in correſpondence, a diſtinct degree of glory, layd vp to be poſſeſſed in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This glory is a thing of ſuch incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and ſoueraigne quality and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, as that the Bleſſed Apoſtle ſayth thereof, <hi>That neither the eye hath ſeene,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2</note> 
                  <hi>nor the eare hath heard, nor the heart hath comprehended any ſuch thing as that.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:2348:65"/>A poore mans eye in this world might at eaſe diſcouer a million of times more greatnes and glory, then euer the greateſt, and moſt glorious Monarch did enioy. And yet a mans eye may be ſayd ſcarce able to ſee any thing, if it be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the infinitenes of thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, whereof we may haue newes by our eares. For who can ſee ſo many things, as the tongue of others can tell him of? But yet, neither can al that, which we may euen heare, hold any manner of proportion with thoſe worlds of other things, which by the faculties of our minde, we may conceaue. For when all is ſeene which can be ſhewed, &amp; when all is heard which can be tould, it remaines for vs to imagine other manner of things then all thoſe; and to multiply and frame by fancy, vpon a minutes warning, both innumerable more ſpecies, and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably more excellent, then thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer were. So that it is no meane expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for the Bleſſed Apoſtle to vſe, when he ſaith that the glory and ioy of heauen, doth excell all that which can be ſeene or heard by the ſenſe, or which can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be conceaued by the hart of man, And yet meanes of high euen by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:2348:65"/>
the Apoſtle himſelfe dares not venture or preſume to tell vs how great thoſe ioyes are; but only, that other things are not ſo great as they. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may rather be accounted to deliuer what they are not, then what they are.</p>
               <p>This ioy and glory, is ſo high, and great, and deepe as that one inſtant ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of would incomparably exceede and out ſtrip, in true account, all the ſenſuall ioy and glory, which hath beene found and felt, by all the mortall creatures of fleſh and bloud put togeather, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the world till the end thereof; though all that glory and ioy, could be caſt and ſummed vp into one ſingle act of glorying, and enioying. For the honour and pleaſure of this world, carryes noe proportion at all, with that of the next, any more then idle dreames doe with ſtrong truthes, or vaine ſhadowes with ſubſtance, which is ſubſtance indeede. For in this life, whatſoeuer delight is felt, the minde of man is ſtill too hard for the body, and ouer works it; &amp; doth ſecretly, either giue or take a kind of lye and inſatisfaction, euen in the topp of all the greateſt pleaſure which it feeles, though dull people vnderſtand not, or
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:2348:66"/>
obſerue not this. But if, for any one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, a ſoule could haue any one glimpſe of celeſtiall bliſſe, and be ingulfed with all the facultyes thereof, vpon an obiect of ſuch infinite perfection, as God is, and that this were done, without the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, or interpretation of any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but that the whole ſoule might touch and mingle and vnite it ſelfe for that inſtant with that ſoueraigne obiecte; O how fully would the ſoule be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied! O how baſe, &amp; how beaſtiall would all the delight and glory of this world, both appeare and be, in reſpect of that!</p>
               <p>We may ſee ſome traces of this truth, by a conſideration of thoſe ſupernatural viſitations, and ſpirituall illuſtrations, &amp; eleuations, whereby our Lord hath been pleaſed to deſcend into the ſoules of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable ſeruants and Spouſes of his, euen in this life; that ſo they might be enabled to take in, as it were ſome little ſent and ayre of that eternall bliſſe, which is prepared for them in the next. Yea &amp; how many haue there beene, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, being all immerſed in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite of terrene honour, and delight, haue by the meanes of ſome one cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall viſitation, been inſtantly, and for
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:2348:66"/>
euer eſtranged (and that with extreme contempt) from the care of all the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ioye and greatnes, which this world was able to afford them, ane haue been fixed with a perpetuall eye, vpon the moſt ardent loue, and moſt loyall faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruice of our Lord God.</p>
               <p>The ſtoryes of our Saints liues, and our owne experience in conuerſation with ſpirituall perſons, which through the goodnes of God are neuer wanting in his holy Catholicke Church, hath made vs not only ſee this truth, but euen as it were, to touch it with our fingers ends. And yet there can be no doubt, but that all the ſpirituall viſitations, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations, and extaſies, and rapts, which euer ſhall be, or haue bene felt and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this life, by all the ſeruants of God, (and yet in ſome one of them, we know that <hi>S. Paule</hi> was taken vp into the third heauen, and that he was poſſeſſed with the vnderſtanding and feeling of ſo high myſteries, as it was neither lawfull, not poſſible for man to expreſſe) are moſt poore and meane thinges in compariſon of any one moment of ioy in Heauen. And the reaſon hereof is cleare. For whatſoeuer ſpirituall gift is imparted in
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:2348:67"/>
this life, is but by image and repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but in the next, it is in ſubſtance, and face to face, with God himſelfe, where he is ſeene, as he is indeede.</p>
               <p>If then one inſtant of celeſtiall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be not only ſo farre exceeding all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ioy and pleaſure, which is but duſt and traſh, being compared with that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but that alſo euen the higheſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall guſt and ioy, which is experime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this life, be not able once to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, in ſight of one moment of that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ioye, which is felt in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (though it be but for one inſtant) how infinitely muſt we find our ſelues obliged to this immortal God of ours, who hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed, not to ty vs to inſtants of time, in the fruition of that glory; but to enlarge and extend it, I ſay not to yeares, or ages, or worlds of time, but as farre as perfect eternity it ſelfe? In compariſon whereof the time of all this world, from <hi>Adam</hi> to this day, and a million of millions as much time as that, and as many more millions as all the hearts of all men can comprehend and count, are not ſo much in durance, as one minute is, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with all thoſe millio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of time. And yet all this eternity of ſuch glory, as I
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:2348:67"/>
haue deſcribed, is vouchſafed to vs by the inexhauſted goodnes of our Lord God for hauing produced any one ſingle acte of Faith and Loue, which yet we ſee may be innumerably multiplied with ſo much caſe. For any one ſingle thought, which is directed to the glory of our Lord God, doth increaſe the ſame grace in our ſoules, and conſequently layes vp a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct degree of that eternall glory, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue ſpoken. So that, it is a cleare and conſtant truth, that for euery other good thought (which may be conceaued in any one moment of time) we ſhall haue an increaſe of eternall glory, in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct degree, beyond that which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we ſhould haue had; and we ſhall for euer ſee more perfectly the immortall Eſſence of Almighty God, and loue it more, and enioy it more, then we ſhould haue done, if we had not produced that one ſingle act of minde, which yet (as I ſayd) may be done by any ignorant or ſilly creature in the world, in any one moment of his time. And yet withall, we are ſo miſerable, as not to lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that this time ſhould be loſt, not only vpon toyes, and conſequently vpon not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing this ſtocke of immortall treaſure;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:2348:68"/>
but euen vpon committing of ſinnes, which doe no thing but horde vp an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of immenſe torments for vs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteede thereof.</p>
               <p>We Catholickes muſt be thankefull, and beg grace withall, that we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue where we are; and we muſt beg it alſo for ſuch others, as are not, and will not be ſo happy yet; to the end that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning all the vaine delights and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of this world, which may intice them, and all the diſaduantages &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles which may threaten them, they may giue themſelues vp now at laſt, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued into the boſome, of the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Apoſtolicke Romane Church; and ſo, to be embraced by thoſe ſtrong armes of that diuine protection and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, which Chriſt our Lord, her Spouſe, hath endewed her with, for the ſauing of thoſe ſoules, for which he died. Our Lord God make them ſo happy, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue this bleſſing: and let all his Saints and Angels euer glofiry his holy name, for hauing imparted it to vs.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2348:68"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAPTER 1.</label>
THAT Catholickes are both improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and vniuſtly charged, with lacke of Charity, for affirming that Proteſtancy vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented deſtroyes ſaluation.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chapter 2.</label>
Of the intention of Catholickes, when they ſay that Protestancy vnrepented deſtroies ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, &amp; how that ſpeech is to be vnderstood.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chapter 3.</label>
That our ſaying; that Protestancy vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented destroies ſaluation, proceedes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> want of Charity in vs, is no leſſe vntrue (becauſe there is but one true Church) then already I haue shewed it to be improbable; and first this is proued by holy Scripture.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chapter 4.</label>
The expreſſe vnity of the Church is alſo proued by the authority of the Fathers of the moſt primitiue times.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chapter 5.</label>
It is proued both by holy Scriptures, &amp; Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb facs="tcp:2348:69"/>
that out of this one true Church of Christ our Lord, no ſaluation is to be found.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chapter 6.</label>
That both Catholickes &amp; Protesta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not poſsibly be accompted to be of one &amp; the ſame Religion, Faith, and Church.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chapter 7.</label>
Three obiections ar auoided, which they make againſt vs, to diſproue our vnity in faith amongst our ſelues; and ſo alſo is an allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about Fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal, points of faith wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they would shewe, that they hold as much vnity both with the Fathers, and with the Lutherans, yea and euen with vs Catholickes at this day, as they are bound to maintaine.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chapter 8.</label>
That Protestants haue no reaſon, in alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the diſtinction of fundamentall and not fundamentall points of faith, as intending to proue thereby, that they are in vnity, with the Fathers of the Primitiue Church, or of their fellow brethren the Lutherans, yea and ſome times with Catholickes at this day.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chapter 9.</label>
That Protestants neither do, nor dare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what are their fundamentall points of faith; wherby yet they would pretend that they liue in the communion of the only one true Church of our Lord.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2348:69"/>
                  <label>Chapter 10.</label>
A recapitulation of the whole diſcourſe, wherein followes, vpon the confeſsion of both parties, that the Catholickes and Proteſtants be not both of them ſauable in their ſeueral Religions without repentance thereof before they dye; and Catholickes must therefore be no longer held vncharitable, for ſaying ſo: but thoſe Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are shewed to be Libertines, who ſay the contrary.</item>
               <item>The Concluſion.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:2348:70"/>
            <head>FAVLTES ESCAPED in the printing.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Faultes</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Corrected</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pag. 8 l. 1 as man</cell>
                     <cell>as a man</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17 l. 2 we owne</cell>
                     <cell>we owe</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21 l. 29 <hi>hadu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commaded</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>had commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24 l. 26 perſiſting</cell>
                     <cell>perſiſting</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>30 l. 24 did it much</cell>
                     <cell>did it with much</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32 l. 28 doctrine or</cell>
                     <cell>doctrine of</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>36 l. 16 <hi>of of eternall</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>of eternall</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>38 l. 1. who forſake</cell>
                     <cell>who forſakes</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>41 l. 2 theſe Saint elwhere</cell>
                     <cell>the Saint elſe where</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>51 l. 10 to condemned</cell>
                     <cell>to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>55 l. 28 title of booke</cell>
                     <cell>title of a booke</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>68 l. 9 particular ſtudied</cell>
                     <cell>particularly ſtudied</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>70 l. 22 or argumt</cell>
                     <cell>or argument</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>93 l. 9 execrable of</cell>
                     <cell>execrable aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>101 l. 4. of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſoules</cell>
                     <cell>of our ſoules</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>110 l 6 and <hi>Polycarpe</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>and S. <hi>Polycarpe</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>l. 28 <hi>ſcoffe as vs</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſcoffe at vs</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>117 l. 17 firſt cleare</cell>
                     <cell>firſt cleared</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>119 l. 28 caſe, chat</cell>
                     <cell>caſe, that</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>124 l. 29 And yet meanes of high euen by this</cell>
                     <cell>And yet euen by this meanes of high.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2348:70"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
